<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Albania or, Certaine concernments of Great Britanny. With an explication of the present state thereof; truely represented under the faigned person of Albania. / By George Raleigh.</title>
            <author>Raleigh, George, b. 1600?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 151 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91834</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R150</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E179_16</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7782</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99873188</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99873188</idno>
            <idno type="VID">125649</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91834)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 125649)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 31:E179[16])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Albania or, Certaine concernments of Great Britanny. With an explication of the present state thereof; truely represented under the faigned person of Albania. / By George Raleigh.</title>
                  <author>Raleigh, George, b. 1600?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 59, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Sweeting, and are to be sold at his shop, at the signe of the Angell, in Popes-head-Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:125649:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:125649:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ALBANIA: OR, <hi>CERTAINE</hi> CONCERNMENTS OF GREAT BRITANNY.</p>
            <p>WITH An Explication of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſtate thereof; Truely repreſented under the faigned Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of <hi>ALBANIA.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY GEORGE RALEIGH.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Sed &amp; bene velle meretur veniam,</hi> 
               <bibl>Cicero.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Sweeting,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop, at the ſigne of the <hi>Angell,</hi> in Popes-head-Alley. 1641.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:125649:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:125649:2"/>
            <head>TO THE KINGS MOST EXCELLENT MAIESTIE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">K</seg>INGS (Mighty Soveraigne) like Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets in their Orbes (under that <hi>Primum Mobile,</hi> from whence all beings derive their exiſtence and continuance) are ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in their ſeverall Thrones, to rule and guide the people committed to their charge by the ſweet influence of Love, and unreprovable motion of their juſtice; which axiome of State more eſpecially di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects it ſelfe to your Majeſties conſideration, who (as the Sunne in reſpect of other Luminaries) do ſhine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in a ſpheare of ſuch eminency, as beſides the unparalleld luſtre it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines at home, doth communicate its ſplendor to forraine parts, as a patterne for the greateſt Potentates.</p>
            <p>And hereupon, as according to the propinquity or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Sunne in its annuall peregrination, the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary bodies receive their augmentation, or diminution accordingly: ſo are the hearts of all your loyall Subjects il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminated with the preſence of this gracious aſpect, and miſerably overſhadowed with ſorrow in the leaſt abſence thereof.</p>
            <p>But bleare eyes are no fit objects for ſuch bright rayes, nor are meane conceits allowable ſubjects for Royall appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions;
<pb facs="tcp:125649:3"/>
nevertheleſſe, as the Sunne loſeth nothing of its ſplendor, when it ſo farre declines in its beames, to kiſſe the low ſhrubs as well as the tall Cedars, and though it be alike diffuſive to all, yet admits no taint in the touch of the vileſt creature: So if your Majeſty vouchſafe to caſt downe a gracious eye on the humble preſent of your meaneſt Subject (as from the hand of a more able giver) your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe cannot ſuffer much in this abaſement, but your good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſhall ſhew it ſelfe tranſparent, and like that glorious mirrour of all beautifull perfections.</p>
            <p>Howſoever I durſt not to have preſumed thus high up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any imagination that your Majeſty wanted farre better information or adviſe, eſpecially from ſo honorable an Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly as that of the preſent Parliament; but as in a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall obſtruction of water currents, it is naturall for the ſhalloweſt Brookes as deepeſt Rivers, to ſeeke way for their paſſage; likewiſe in a common calamity, the meaneſt (who are commonly the firſt ſufferers) cannot be blamed for put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a finger to the griefe, nor juſtly conſtrained to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe their complaints in ſilence onely. But if my intentions have faulted in the matter or manner, (being errors of skil not will) I beſeech your Majeſty ſo farre to beare with either, as may pardon the preſumption of him that is a dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Orator for your Majeſties temporall, and eternall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe;</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>George Raleigh.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:125649:3"/>
            <head>ALBANIA, <hi>OR,</hi> Certaine Concernements of GREAT BRITANNIE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Las poore Princeſſe <hi>Megala!</hi> (a Mirrour to ſhew that there is no contentment to be ſought for in earthly tranſitories) ſometimes happy in thy private for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, more happy to have lived by lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Neighbours, in a Country rich in large Provinces, potent in free States, and Princes; glorious in magnificent Cities, ſtately Temples, goodly Palla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and large Edifices; adorned with delectable Groves, and Walkes for the Muſes; fenced with ſtrong Caſtles, Citta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dells, and Bulwarkes; graced with delightſome Gardens, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Arbours, Chryſtall Fountaines, artificiall Columnes, Pyramids, Spires, Obeliskes; priviledged with honorable Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, and immunities; famous for great Marts, inventive Craftſ-men; canopyed as it were, in divers parts, with faire Woods, and ſpacious Forreſts, carpeted (if I may ſo ſpeake) with flowry Meadowes, and verdant Paſtures; hung round about with Vineyards, and Embroydered with Corne-fields;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:125649:4"/>
inlayd with rich minerals; bordered with lofty Mountaines, pleaſant Vallies, and Rivers abounding in moſt ſorts of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licate Fiſh, and for depth, capable of Veſſells of ſufficient bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, for the conveyance of its owne, and Forraine Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie.</p>
            <p>Alaſſe! did I ſay, ſometimes ſo happy, and muſt now ſay, (<hi>Sic tranſit gloria mundi</hi>)</p>
            <lg>
               <l>So in the turning of a glaſſe,</l>
               <l>All worldly glory ſoone doth paſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Unfortunate, and moſt miſerable <hi>Megala,</hi> in this laſt century of yeares, having ſpent more then an Age in pertinacious en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counters, inteſtine Warres, and tragicall turmoyles; lying as it were all this while, weltring in the blood of no leſſe then a million of Chriſtian Soules, and Martiall ſpirits; by meanes whereof, the Plague, and Famine (ſeconding the cruelty of the Sword) hath uſhered in the maſſacring and mourning of thy Nobles, the lamentable ſhrikes and cries of Widdowes, and Orphanes, the brutiſh raviſhment of grave Matrons, and faire Virgins, the inhumane daſhing in pieces of Infants and ſucklings, the torturing of all ſorts of people, by worſe dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolicall cruelties, then a Turke, or Inquiſition doe put in practiſe: So that</p>
            <lg>
               <head>Talia fando quis temperet a lachymis!</head>
               <l>To ſpeake of this,</l>
               <l>What griefe it is!</l>
            </lg>
            <p>And of theſe heavy misfortunes, what end doth there yet appeare? how many ſpectators, how few true compaſſioners have there beene? whiles on one ſide, the over-weening <hi>Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linus</hi> (whoſe power makes the juſtneſſe of his quarrell, and his quarrell is the cauſe of all theſe troubles) ſtrengthened with the confederacy and ayd of potent Allies, eſpecially by that of the Lord of the ſilver Mountaines, animated thereto by the benediction and encouragement of that arch-enemy of true Religion, the great Prince of ceremonies, and Key-keeper of <hi>Idolana</hi> (a City ſometimes very famous for worthy <hi>Heroes,</hi> and glorious Martyrs, when vertue and verity were in moſt requeſt, and now as notorious for ſuperſtitious orders of ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant and lazy votaries, as infamous for allowed brothells, of leud queanes and ſtrumpets.) But of all the rabble that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends upon their Demi-god <hi>Regicida,</hi> a ravening Wolfe in a
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:125649:4"/>
Sheepes habit, a ſubtle pated agent in politique affaires (that common State medlar, never good till rotten) an Incendiary well knowne in Princes Courts, and moſt parts of the habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble world, that have beene hitherto diſcovered, one that is ever caſting firebrands of Treaſon, and ſedition, whereſoever he comes, or is any while admitted, though moſt times the ſparkes flye about his owne eares, and that whiles he is even ready to put fire to his powder-plots, and is at the heighth of his Machinations, whoſe impudence is ſuch, that the often and manifeſt diſcovery of his treacherous deſignes, doth no whit ſhame or diſcourage him from the like attempts; Upon the firſt occaſion, onely intimate your deſires by ſome large gift, or proffer, and you have him with his aſſociates (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of there are ſwarmes in <hi>Verana,</hi> be the action never ſo dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous or unwarrantable) preſt and ſerviceable for the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: and therefore the Princes of <hi>Verana,</hi> eſpecially the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narches of the bleſſed Iſland, and Lilly fields, have little cauſe to favour his perſon, or to truſt to his flatteries.</p>
            <p>But by what an ill ſubject am I carryed, from the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of what I was ſpeaking, touching <hi>Aquilinus,</hi> who lookes upon the diſtreſſes of <hi>Megala,</hi> with an Eagles eye; to prey upon her liberties, and faſten her in the chaine of a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall ſlavery: And whereas that great Prince, who diſplayes the Queene of Flowers in his Enſignes, caſts an eye towards her at ſome diſtance, it is not ſo much in compaſſion of her dejected eſtate, as of the riſing greatneſſe of his ambitious competitour, who ſeekes by the ruine of all his Neighbours, to ſet up a Throne for himſelfe, and his houſe of abſolute Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piry<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> over all the Principalities in <hi>Verana,</hi> whiles others, which ſtand in oppoſition to his deſignes, wiſh well to the diſconſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late Princeſſe, but having not power anſwerable to their will, muſt, for their owne eaſe and quiet, of neceſſity, ſit downe as they may, and expect the event with patience.</p>
            <p>But that the peereleſſe <hi>Albania,</hi> of all others, ſhould be ſo indulgent to her ſelfe contentments, and be a looker on with dry eyes, and not take more to heart the burning of a Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours houſe, allyed to her by more than the tyes of ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry relations, through a branch iſſued out of the ſame ſtocke with her Soveraigne, but lamentably afflicted, through the wracke and loſſe of her <hi>Rheniſh</hi> darling, it ſeemes wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:125649:5"/>
and that ſhe is ſo ſenſleſſe of the wound that is given her through the ſides of that Princeſſe, and her Royall off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring. And I feare it is too much her fault, herein common with other Nations, whom long Peace and Proſperity hath caſt into a Lethargy of deepe ſecurity, to applaud their owne happineſſe, and ſwelling there with to behold forraine ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities, (as newes not credible, or for a nine dayes won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) with the eyes of contempt and diſgrace, nothing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning their pitty, or regard; making an ill uſe thereof to juſtifie themſelves as more righteous, and intereſſed in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the Almighty (committing notwithſtanding the ſame, or like ſinnes, of a worſe nature and higher degree) upon no other ground but that of Preſcription, for the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of ſo much pleaſure and plenty, ſo long without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batement, or interruption, together with immunity and freedome from the puniſhment their Neighbours have this while fallen into; whereas they might with more reaſon, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect and feare, and by wofull arguments conclude, that the dregges of vengeance are reſerved in the cup of the Divine ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice (ſuch a ſting hath ſinne in it, and ſo bitter a potion doth it compound) for theſe wretches to ſucke out to the laſt drop, who make light of ſo gracious examples, and are regardleſſe of ſuch unuſuall mercies and many warnings af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded to them, ſo that there remaines nothing but timely repentance, to barre the draught, which though it reliſh as an unſavoury pill to a dainty pallate, yet to the more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiderate, and ſuch as are ſenſible of their eſtate and deſerts, I may not unfitly commend that of the Poet:</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Sed &amp; haec meminiſſe juvabit.</l>
               <l>Often to minde on this,</l>
               <l>Will not be much amiſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Ah! careleſſe, forgetfull <hi>Albania:</hi> how is it poſſible, that a Nation as thine, ſurrounded with an Ocean of all delights, and Crowned with a <hi>Cornu copia</hi> of the greateſt bleſſings, free from inteſtine mutinies, and forraine invaſions hitherto (notwithſtanding theſe bold affronts enterpriſed with better reſolution then followed with ſucceſſe) ſhould be thus un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankeful? Tell me, can the Records of any people under the ſonne, ſpeake of ſuch a continued happineſſe as theirs, without ſome alteration? Call to minde, <hi>Albania,</hi> that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:125649:5"/>
benefit from Heaven was conferred upon thy Land, in its deliverance from the bondage and ſlavery of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious <hi>Idolana,</hi> whereby the light of Gods true Worſhip hath ſhined upon thee in ſuch cleareneſſe, as the Sunne at noone day; and if therefore thy body were every day on the Altar of thankeſgiving conſumed to aſhes, it would be all too little for a gratulatory ſacrifice: for now</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Ceſſant oracula Delphis.</l>
               <l>All Pagan trumperies,</l>
               <l>Are fled and fained lies.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>The bleſſed Iſland may with much comfort ſay, There are no ſacrifices in me for gods, made, or created of mortall ſeed, ſuch as proceed from the ſame mould, live in the ſame clay, and returne into the ſame duſt, my people attribute no protection of reaſonable, or unreaſonable creatures; Men, Nations, Cities, Temples, to created ſubſtances; neither <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter, Apollo, Mars, Venus,</hi> nor any of the male or female Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, have any domination over our Worſhip: whether <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter Hammon,</hi> or <hi>Jupiter</hi> of <hi>Creete, Mercury</hi> of <hi>Athens, Venus</hi> of <hi>Paphos, Diana</hi> of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> be the Patrons and Patroneſſes of ſuch places, comes not within our Creed: whether <hi>Aeſoulapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> have the governance of Phyſitians, <hi>Mars</hi> of Souldiers, <hi>Pan</hi> of Shepherds, <hi>Ceres</hi> of Husbandmen, or <hi>Lucina</hi> be the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens goddeſſe Midwife; as we abhorre the names, ſo are we ignorant of the perſons: the <hi>Dryades, Hamadryades, Nereides</hi> have left our Springs: The <hi>Sylvanes, Fawnes,</hi> and <hi>Satyres</hi> have forſaken our Woods, ever ſince the vayled ſiſters, and their cowled brethren were turned out of their cloyſters: and we have heard no tales of Elves, Hobgoblins, Fairies, and Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin-good fellowes: <hi>Albania</hi> is as free of Idolatrous Rites and Ceremonies, as ſhe is of Beares, Wolves, and other noyſome creatures.</p>
            <p>But (thankes be to the Almighty) we have the Worſhip of the onely eternall Deity, in Truth and Spirit, and ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Doctrine in the Fundamentalls, concerning right be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leife and practice, conſenting in a ſweet harmony with the other Churches of <hi>Verana,</hi> adorned with the decency of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline (inſtituted by a pious Prince, and Councell) accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the purity of the primitive patterne, (as neere as the times would permit) beſides dignities, priviledges, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:125649:6"/>
allotted to the Prelates, and other Miniſters of the Sacred Oracles (although perchance, not with that equall diſtribution, as admits not a juſt complaint, and requires a due conſideration for redreſſe) to encourage them in their ſtudies, and diligences, according to their degrees and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings. And if any abuſe themſelves in their demeanours, or duties, (for they are men, and may erre) the fault and penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ought to reflect upon the perſons, and not the Function.</p>
            <p>And farther had this Reformation extended, but that the death of that hopefull young Prince (<hi>Quo nulla aetas tulit me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liorem;</hi> without diſparagement to any be it ſpoken) and therefore fitly paralleld with the good <hi>Joſias,</hi> and by a Zelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>typian of ſubtle judgement, termed, <hi>The Mirrour and prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy of Princes;</hi> haſtened (as 'tis thought) by ſome treacherous practices, gave a period to theſe expectations.</p>
            <p>And although, after the deceaſe of this Worthy, in the Raigne of his elder ſiſter (a Lady of a temper milde enough by nature, had it not beene wreſted by ill counſell: and a ſtocke good enough to have borne better fruite, had it not beene ill grafted) there aroſe many blacke clouds in our Horizon, which obſcured the sky, and through the perſwaſion of ill adviſed heads, and her too flexible yeeldings, diſſolved in ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taracts of bloud, with ſuch violence (the flaſhes of Lightning which brake through, menacing to ſet Religion all on a flame) that they ſeemed to beare downe the ground-worke of all former proceedings before them: Yet ever bleſſed be the Omnipotent over-ruler, and diſpoſer of the greateſt Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentates, and their purpoſes; This <hi>ſanguis Martyrum,</hi> proved to be but <hi>ſemen Eccleſiae,</hi> and the ſparks that iſſued from the bone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fires, in which ſo many learned and holy men fryed for the witneſſing of their Profeſſion, flew into the eyes of their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors, and the ſhafts, they thus madly darted at Heaven, and the ſtarres, rebounded into their owne boſomes with a vengeance, whiles their Tyranny and lives ended ſhortly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, moſt of them in a fearefull and horrible manner.</p>
            <p>And yet their incredulous abetters will not be ſo wiſe to take warning by ſuch evident examples, imputing Gods juſt Judgements, either to ſecond cauſes, or wrong ends; bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the relation with the credit of a Fable or Legend: as hereby willing rather to loſe themſelves, then foregoe any
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:125649:6"/>
antiquated errour, from the corruption of former times and ignorance to them conveyed.</p>
            <p>But this miſt being vaniſhed, the Sun began to ſhine againe, when the Scepter and true Religion paſſed under the ſway of <hi>Leoniſſa</hi> (incomparable <hi>Leoniſſa</hi>) a Princeſſe of an Heroicke ſpirit, and much differing in diſpoſition and beleife from her ſiſter, ſo that ſhe might juſtly be termed, <hi>The Mirrour of her ſex, and glory of her Kingdome;</hi> whoſe excellencies (ſaith a worthy ſervant of hers, without flattery) may well be admired, but cannot be related in any meaſure, proportionable to the worth of their perfections. She was endowed with rare gifts of Nature; and adorned with exquiſite ornaments of Art; well skilled in Languages, and in the Sciences; and could readily and pithily anſwer Embaſſadors and Orators in their ſeverall Dialects. As concerning her behaviour, ſhe was affa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and loving, and therefore highly beloved of all her good Subjects; ſhe was feared, and envyed of her enemies, reſpected and ſollicited by her Neighbours, whom, in their neceſſity, ſhe divers times relieved, with Men, Monies, and Munition: ſhe was ſucceſſefull in all her enterprizes, victorious alwayes in her attempts, either by ſea or Land; and ſafegarded from ſo many treaſons and conſpiracies againſt her perſon and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion by the divine providence, that it ſeemed to worke mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles in her defence, and to point with the finger that ſhee maintained his cauſe whom he thus protected; and that as ſhe ſubjected her actions to his glory, he enclined her ſubjects to loyall obedience, and willing ſupplyes; ſo that her Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer was alwayes well ſtored, and her people nothing grieved; for no new or extraordinary taxes were impoſed, but by the way of a generall Aſſembly, that was readily gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, which was reaſonably required, and the giver was able enough, and not the leſſe willing to give againe, when occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on required.</p>
            <p>In this manner raigned this vertuous Empreſſe, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to the yeares of an aged Matron, but dyed a religious Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, and all good men ſhed teares at her Exequies: Her loſſe was lamented of all, but ſuch as were enemies to truth and the Religion ſhe profeſſed, and yet maugre the thunderbolts and bug-beares of <hi>Idolana,</hi> the malicious practices and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of <hi>Glorioſa,</hi> the calumnies of detracting <hi>Regicida,</hi> darted
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:125649:7"/>
at her perſon, purpoſed againſt her Kingdome, and leveld at her birth and actions, thoſe braving cenſures of the one vaniſhed into the ayre, and (as a candle extinguiſhed) left nothing behinde them but a ſtinking ſnuffe. The invincible actions of the ſecond were ſhamefully, and (this was Gods owne do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) totally defeated; but the virulency of the laſt returned the cup of venome into his owne hand, and cauſed him to drinke his bane therein, either wretchedly in other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, as a fugitive, or at home deſperately on the gallowes, as a traytor, whileſt a name remaines to her of happy memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and will be in all ages as a precious oyntment ſpread upon the face of the whole earth.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Soloccubuit, nox nulla ſequnta eſt.</l>
               <l>The Sunne was gone,</l>
               <l>But night came none.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>The Prince was changed, the happineſſe remained. For when the want of iſſue ſeemed to put a maske on all faces, and to compaſſe the Region of all hearts with a doubtfull trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, and jealouſie of the next ſucceſſion; behold, (without tumult or delay) a Lion Rampant of the Royall Stocke, comes out of the <hi>North,</hi> and ſteps into the Throne with generall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe, and (to double the content) brings along with him another Kingdome, like in complection and profeſſion, to the hopes of a perpetuall Union (May they never attaine their wiſhes which ſeeke the diſcontinuance hereof, to the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine of either!)</p>
            <p>In this Princes perſon (being nurſed at <hi>Helicon,</hi> and bred on <hi>Pernaſſus</hi>) the Graces and Muſes might well be ſaid to meete together, or (if <hi>Platoes Metempſychoſis</hi> were admitted) that the ſoule of <hi>Paleſtina's</hi> Royall Prophet, and harmonious <hi>Pſalmographiſt</hi> had animated it he was a judicious Divine, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſive Oratour, and ingenious Poet; very well skilled was he in the interpretation of ſacred Oracles, ſingularly dexte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous in the reſolution of doubts, and determination of hard queſtions, and points of difficulty; powerfully able in cruſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the controverſies, and untwiſting the <hi>Gordian</hi> knots of Cardinall Oppoſites; and that I faine nothing herein, or flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in any ſort, his Treatiſes are ſufficient Apologiſts, and witneſſes: (<hi>Let good Princes ever have the honour of their deſerts</hi>) He eaſily bore away the Palme from all other of his ranke,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:125649:7"/>
contemporary or of preceding ages. The truth is, he was not addicted <hi>tam Marti, quam Mercurio,</hi> he made more uſe of his pen than of his ſword; neither can this any whit derogate from his commendation, or leſſen the worth of his Judgment.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Nulla ſalus bello, Pacem te poſcimus omnes.</l>
               <l>No ſafety is in Warre,</l>
               <l>For Peace all ſuters are.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>None but ſuch as are of a turbulent ſpirit, or ignorant what Warre is, love to play the beaſts and inhumanely gore each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for to ſatisfie ſome carnall appetite of ambition, Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, or revenge; The Souldier indeed will fight valiant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, onely in a good cauſe, being neceſſitated thereto, either for Gods glory, or the Kingdomes ſafety. Otherwiſe, if the undertaking reſpect ſome private ſenſuall end, the action can be no other then brutiſh and reaſonleſſe, and here it is much better to purchaſe peace, though at a deere rate, then to begin a quarrell, though with much advantage. The nobleſt victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is that which is gotten without blood-ſhed; for the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy of the braine more than ſtrength of arme is requiſite in an accompliſhed Captaine, and beſt deſerves the Coronet: Men were not made to act Tragedies, nor to make the world a ſhambles for humane ſlaughters, ſaith a reverend man, and therefore that <hi>Worthy</hi> was well adviſed, and his conſideration merited high Commendation, who had rather ſave one of his Subjects lives, then kill a thouſand of his enemies: and that Emperour was farre from a bloody diſpoſition, whoſe uſe was to hang out a white, next a blacke, ere he was forced to put forth the red flagge: ſignifying thereby that he was more deſirous, and would uſe all meanes to ſave, rather than deſtroy his enemy.</p>
            <p>And with theſe or the like Precedents his late Majeſty in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, bent all his endeavours for the compoſure of thoſe turmoyles and differences which unhappily fell out betwixt the Princes (allies and confederates with him) in his time, whoſe earneſtneſſe herein too much led him into the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of a ſtrangers ſoothings, and ſomewhat tranſported him (I confeſſe) beyond his owne inclination, to be more ſevere in Juſtice againſt his owne, then otherwiſe he would have beene: Which afterwards (as ſome Objécts are beſt diſcerned at a farther diſtance) he well perceived with ſome
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:125649:8"/>
regret, and much blamed the fouleneſſe of their ingratitude, who abuſed his favours to the ſtaine of his other vertues: how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever his ayme was nevertheleſſe praiſeworthy, in framing a ſilver Bridge for all enmities to paſſe over, whereby he pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed the bleſſed Title of <hi>Peacemaker,</hi> and therewith in all quiet manner ended a happy raigne and life together.</p>
            <p>From <hi>whoſe</hi> aſhes is ſprung the <hi>Phoenix,</hi> on whoſe beauty all the eyes of the bleſſed Iſland are now caſt, and for whoſe hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, all the deſires and prayers of the vertuouſly minded, are daily ſent to the <hi>Throne of Grace.</hi> A Prince (not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale or palliate the Truth, where ſo manifeſt Authority war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants) as for Temperance, Continence, Juſtice, Clemency, Bountifullneſſe, and ſuch like vertues, amongſt his equalls claimes the priority: and from his Subjects the choyſeſt of Obedience with all dutifull affections.</p>
            <p>And now whiles under the wings of this unmatched Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragon, ſits the glad <hi>Albania</hi> ſecure from feare or danger, and at her leaſure contemplates (as not ſuſpecting any change) on the manifold kindes of happineſſe, ſhe formerly, and now is wrapped in; and making a ſhort progreſſe through her Country, in conceit to view the particular delights thereof, and withall including the Seas round about, within the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference of her thoughts; ſhe ſeemed to ſee <hi>Neptune</hi> with both his armes, hugging and embracing the bleſſed Iſland as the darling of his delights, and on his Mantle of blew (as the favour of his Miſtreſſe) he wore a chaine of goodly ſhips, and ſuch as no Sea within his vaſt and ample dominions, could ever make ſhew of the like, either for ſhape or uſe, a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacle (conſidering the workemanſhip and munition) full of pleaſure and terrour together: amongſt which one So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne, as <hi>Diana</hi> amongſt her Nymphes,</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Velut inter Stellas</l>
               <l>Lima minores,</l>
               <l>As to our ſight by farre</l>
               <l>The Moone exceedes each Starre,</l>
            </lg>
            <p>gave ſuch a luſtre of worth in her eminency above the reſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to the eye of the judicious beholder, that ſhe might be reputed well worthy of her name, and fit to be ſervant onely to her great Maſter, and not unbeſeeming his eſpeciall regard. On
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:125649:8"/>
which rare object <hi>Albania</hi> would longer have ſtaid her ſight and wonder, but that the Marine Commander with his Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, was forcing ſundry ſorts of fiſhes in ſcoales, to ſhore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, where <hi>Triton</hi> ſummoned his ſhell-ſubjects to joyne with them, and in numberleſſe troopes (the uſe nothing di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhing the encreaſe, oh the goodneſſe of our mercifull and bountifull God!) to attend there for the reliefe of the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants: and this cauſed her to draw the eyes of her medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions thitherwards, and to magnifie the Divine Providence, which had for every ſeaſon fitting, ſtored her Coaſtes with ſo great abundance and variety of ſuch delicate ſuſtenance. And notwithſtanding the plenty, ſhe wiſhed the Fiſherman (a very profitable member in any Common-wealth, and one that if he uſe induſtry with art, deſerves reſpect) would not make ſuch ſpoyle of the young Fry, as is too commonly uſed.</p>
            <p>Next, ſhe conſidered the Harbours, which were many, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, large, and capacious; ſo that a Fleete of numerous ſhips might anchor in them, without danger of any ſtorme or da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, and ſight each of other: although in ſome of them Time began to play the Tyrant, and thruſt bones into their mouthes, ſo that if a bountifull care did not quickly inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it ſelfe for prevention, they might (not without incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience to ſome prime Townes, and their Princes profit) be altogether choaked.</p>
            <p>Into theſe Havens arrived dayly from ſeverall parts of the world, Sayles of ſeverall molds and burthens, whereof ſome of the greater ſort from the Eaſt, unladed Silke, Spices, Drugs, Indicoes, &amp;c. From the South, Wines, Sugar, Oyle, Fruit, Salt, Lyncloth, &amp;c. From the North, Deales, Hempe, Flax, Furres, Tallow, &amp;c. None came empty into their Harbours, but (as Bees into their Hives) with thighes full fraught of pretious and delightfull commodities, whiles others were weighing Anchor to ſet forth with their fine cloathes, ſo much eſteemed in all parts of the world; the Traffique whereof was ſo great in the Low Countryes, that the valew of their Sale yearely at <hi>Antwerpe</hi> (if <hi>Lewes Guichardine</hi> miſreckon not) amounted to more then foure Millions, and the Wooll in his compute which was vented at the Staple in <hi>Burges,</hi> to 500000. <hi>Florens,</hi> (where, by the way, may be eaſily conjectured how great the quantity of this commodity is, by the many Families of Spin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:125649:9"/>
Weavers, Fullers, that in moſt Townes of the bleſſed Iſland are ſet on worke for the making hereof; beſides others were fraughted with the pureſt Tinne, Lead, &amp;c. proviſion of fiſh dryed, pickled, &amp;c. ſo that the ordinary Cuſtomes which accrued to the Crowne from theſe Merchandiſes (truely col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, and faithfully returned) were Revenues of competen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy ſufficient to maintaine the State of more then a petty Prince.</p>
            <p>For the deſence of the Havens, there were ſtrong Caſtles and Bulwarkes, raiſed in the moſt advantageous places, for ſafeguard and offence. And peradventure the charge would not be ſuperfluous, and the worke pay it ſelfe, if the Bayes and Creekes were awed by the like command, and that the Forts which in their outſides preſented ſuch a warlike ſhew to the beholder, were within ſurniſhed with able and truſty Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, with Souldiers and munition anſwerable, encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged by their due pay. And ſhe did hope it was ſo, for her Eye could not pierce through the walles to diſceme the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
            <p>Much taken with theſe objects of pleaſure and delight, was the fortunate <hi>Albania,</hi> and the eye of her contemplation could have ſo journed longer on them, but that the wealthy, gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, and politique Merchants (the feete and hands of the Common-wealth, for exporting and taking in of her ſeverall neceſſaries) who were Owners of the Veſſells, and maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the Trade, drew her thoughts to the place of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence, which by reaſon of the former conſequences ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited to be ſome glorious and well governed City; neither was ſhe much deceived in her imagination, which at her entry within the gates preſented to her ſight, a large frame and Pile of ſtately building, no leſſe pleaſing in the diverſity, then in the uniformity of their ſtructures; but ſhe had almoſt loſt her ſelfe and forgot where ſhe was, when ſhe beheld the Royall Palace and Court adorned with ſo many grave, wiſe, and loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſpirits (and indeed all that would be Courtiers ſhould be thus qualified) beautified with modeſt, native, and Angeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call faces (for Vertue and Beauty, commonly hand together) otherwiſe, the faireſt viſages doe but hide the fouleſt and moſt deformed ſoules; Loath was our glad Lady to remove her gazing from theſe ſpectacles, but that the ſpiring Temples
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:125649:9"/>
built, and in reparation, ſhewed a farre off, as well the piety as magnificence of the Prince who had ſuch reſpect to the ſtructures ſeparated and dedicated to the uſe of holy imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, not onely in garniſhing the walls with commendable ornaments, but eſpecially ſupplying the Deskes, and Pulpits with learned and religious Miniſters: (if it be otherwiſe any where, it is (I preſume) as farre from his knowledge as his deſire; and the more are thoſe to blame, that being ſet in authority for this end, abuſe their truſt, and are negligent in a charge of ſo great importance, committed to them) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by thoſe ſacred Oratories, and Schooles are upon all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions thronged with the preſſe of all ſorts of people that fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent them, to attend on the ſeverall devotions.</p>
            <p>From the Church ſhe went to the Senate, and there much rejoyced to behold the Benches filled with a Prefect and Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity (ſhe tooke them to be in heart as ſhew, and that the ſcarlet outſide, was not lined with a ſackecloth inſide) of a wealthy, Wiſe, and honourable Magiſtracy; and the fruites of their juſtice did in ſome meaſure ſo beſpeake them. Where ſhe ſaw a Beadle carting a Whore, and her Knave Baud, (pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty the Goatiſh Whoremaſter, by favour or meanes ſhould e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape the ſearch and puniſhment ſo narrowly) where ſhe came by a Conſtable ſtocking the Drunkard, and idle Runnagate. (good were it that all ſuſpected perſons ſhould give an account of their Living and employments, and ſo perchance the hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſhould not be ſo often employed to put a halter about the necke of the Murtherer, and Thiefe as he doth: Long hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py and peaceable may the Raigne of our gracious Soveraigne be, who is ſo carefull that his Land be not defiled with blood, and that Juſtice hath ſo free proceeding againſt capitall offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces!) And though this Kingdome, (a happineſſe to be wiſhed, too great to be enjoyed) cannot wholly be rid from leud per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and enormous offenders, (there will be ever lazy droanes to lurke as long as there are buſie Bees to labour) yet the comfort is, there are good Lawes enacted, to ſuppreſſe the common annoyances: and it is his Majeſties Will that they be put in execution. I cannot ſtand to repeate the diverſity of obſervations hereupon, wherewith <hi>Albania</hi> ſtood poſſeſſed, nor how contented ſhe was in viewing that Royall Cittadell and Magazin of munition, and neere thereto a goodly ranke
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:125649:10"/>
of buildings, croſſing a River, in which the ſalt water flowes and ebbes more than a dayes journey from the Mayne, whoſe bankes were beſet with a row of ſumptuous edifices and Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, with other like variety of pleaſing objects, that, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſhe directed her eye, tooke it up with wonder, and this admiration encreaſed the deſire to ſee ſtill farther, but fearing to ſurfet with the delicacies of this City happineſſe, ſhe dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med it would be no ſmall comfort and recreation, to retire in her contemplation ſome while into the Country.</p>
            <p>Where in her travaile, aſcending the Hills of an eaſie riſing, ſhe beheld the ſoyle (on both ſides of her, tranſcendently fruitfull) beſpangled (if I may ſo ſpeake) as the Firmament with Starres, with Golden fleeces, of more value than that the <hi>Argonauts</hi> of old adventured ſo boldly to bring from <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chos;</hi> and therefore the Shepherd Swaine is as famous as his Paſtorals, and not unworthily have Princes, Captaines, and Prieſts, borrowed their reſemblances, and he that was farre above the greateſt of men, diſdained not to ſtile himſelfe the true Shepherd: but deſcending into the Vallyes, ſhe paſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long Greene Meadowes, lying by the Rivers, (each River having its ſtore and variety of delicate Fiſhes) and repleniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſundry ſorts of Cattle for encreaſe and uſe; and in the Plaines, hard by, ſhe ſaw the Country-man tugging at the Plough, and thought it no ſcorne to looke on ſo meane a perſon, and worke, or to viſit his homely Cottage, the one being ſo neceſſary for the being of the State, the other ſtored with proviſion ſufficient to welcome and entertaine his gueſt, as well as the Gentleman of other Countries. Neither did that lofty Poet of his time, any whit deſcend beneath him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, or the dignity of his ſtraine, or thought it any abate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to his Muſe, when he wrote that Poem of the <hi>Georgicke.</hi> But when ſhe beheld the Gentlemans place, conſidered his vaſt, and well contrived buildings, with the pleaſant Arbors, Walkes, Ponds, Parkes, Woods, Lawnes, Chaſes, that he was Maſter of, ſhe could not imagine, but, where was ſuch abundance of all things, to content a worldly deſire, there went ſtore of Hoſpitality with it. And indeed ſo it was <hi>in diebus illis,</hi> but I am ſorry to ſpeake it, Pride and Gaming, two unfruitfull baſtards of eaſe and plenty, like Mothwormes, have of late eaten much into this pretious garment, for want
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:125649:10"/>
of timely circumſpection in the greater part. But <hi>Albania,</hi> walking aſide out of the Common road, ſaw the waſtes full of goodly timber Trees, but (to her no little griefe) with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſaw much felling of the old, and little planting of new, a neglect, which in time (if not prevented) might turne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a lamentable inconvenience, but the plenty of what ſhe ſaw for the preſent, quickly wiped off the miſtruſt, or thought of any future misfortune. And now, though the ſweete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe much abated from the length of the Walke, yet (as ſometimes, when we are glutted with pleaſure, it breedes a loathing to be at ſo much eaſe) <hi>Albania</hi> was by degrees ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in her pace; and had reſted her ſelfe on the next banke but that ſhe was neare by thoſe famous Bathes, ſo curious for their compoſure, ſo wholſome for the vertue of their wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, the Monument of Princely Beneficence. In theſe ſhe bathed her ſelfe once, and againe, and was quickely refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſo that having heard (and what ingenuous ſpirit hath not heard?) of thoſe ſingnalr Academies, ſo much renown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the ſeate, building, maintenance, and learning, that was as it were appropriated to them, that ſhe thought, if ſhe had neglected to take ſome view of them in this perambula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of her minde, ſhe might have beene eſteemed of little judgement, in taking ſo much delight in things that reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the outward ſenſes, many whereof were of uſe but to pleaſe the fancy onely, and to have neglected, or undervalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Arts and Sciences whereby man was to be differenced from another Creature, and one reaſonable man from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, without which a Prince in his Throne, a Captaine in his Tent, a Governour on his Beach, were but as ſo many Statues fit to fill a place, and of little other uſe: for he that hath all the Wealth, Honour, and Pleaſure the World can afford, without the gifts of the minde in ſome meaſure, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſaid to live like a man; whereas, he that is indued with knowledge, the more he retires into himſelfe from all carnall reſpects, ſoares the nearer to a Divine Nature, and is out of the reach of the common miſeries of care and feare, with which meere worldings, and ignorant perſons are ſo often overwhelmed: Upon thoſe conſiderations ſhe went, ſhe ſaw, ſhe heard; but my Oratory is too weake to expreſſe the height of her admiration, and it would require a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:125649:11"/>
rather then a curſory Obſervation, to deſcribe the worth of the Scholler, and the pleaſure of the Schooles. But whiles here ſhe roved at pleaſure in the Tower of her high Conceits, and repoſed her thoughts in the imagination of a like conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall and interrupted happineſſe, a deepe ſleepe of ſecurity ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized her ſenſes, whiles the fancy (ſtill labouring upon the former objects) preſented in a ſtrange dreame, (and dreames many times fall out too true) how vaine and uncertaine is the dependancy upon worldly and temporary felicities; It ſeemed unto her, that in the middeſt of a forward Spring ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, in a faire Sunſhine day, ſhe was recreating her ſelfe in a pleaſant Grove, neare the bubling ſtreame of a Cryſtall Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and ſaw how all the bankes and Borders thereabouts, were beſet with goodly Trees of all ſorts; on the boughes whereof, divers Birds according to their kindes, warbled out ſundry notes of melodious Harmony, and in the thickets, ſhe ſaw the Deere browzing on the tender leaves quietly, and how the ground was all mantled in greene, here and there beſtrewed with flowers, white and red, that bluſhed to ſee themſelves (naked as they were) expoſed to the eye of the beholder; ſo that in this place there wanted nothing to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent the outward ſenſes, but that on a ſuddaine (to ſee the folly of ſuch as ſpend their wits and time in building earthly Tabernacles, and purchaſing worldly inheritances) the bright Sunne became clouded all over, the Hemiſphere darkened, the wind beginneth to blow, a ſtorme came on violently, the drops are powred downe in abundance, ſo that the cleare ſtreames grow muddy, the flowers hang downe their heads, the Birds take their flight, the Beaſts reſort to their ſhelter: And <hi>Albania</hi> (all affrighted at this ſuddaine change, ſtarts, awakes, and looking into the Country round about her, and conſidering how things went in thoſe places, her eye had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly circuited, ſhe found her fancy in this late viſion, to be nothing miſ-enformed, but wondred to ſee the face of all things, as it were in the turne of a hand, ſo ſtrangely altered: for the Shepherd had driven away his flockes out of the field, and put up his pipe, the Husbandman hadleft his Plough, and was at a ſtand, whether he ſhould Till his ground, and how he ſhould pay his Rent, the Gentleman gave over his ſports, and looks after his goods that were diſtrained, the Wife and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:125649:11"/>
Children cry out they are undone, becauſe the poore Labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er that ſhould relieve them is wrongfully troubled, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides his weariſome travailes and expences muſt be content to ſuſtaine the wrong and dammages at his owne charges; the ſurety laments his owne hard fortune, and cruelty of the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing Uſurer, whiles he is conſtrained to pay the debt &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, when the careleſſe principall hath wherewithall to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge it, and is untouched. One ſayes he is unjuſtly puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for neglect of a ſervice whereof (as he ought to have) he had no notice, another exclaimes againſt Officers, that they take too large and extraordinary Fees, and in the meane time no offence committed, nor proved; the Tradeſman blames the Monopoliſt, for engroſſing the ſale of commodities for his owne particular advantage to the dammage of the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall; the Merchant accuſeth the Projector, that unuſuall cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes be impoſed by his meanes; that ſo monies be raiſed, it matters not by what meanes; that the Princes name is uſed, and abuſed for a colour and cloake, and that the generall aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, which were wont to be the onely meanes for ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying the Kings wants, and remedying the Countries grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, hath beene ſo often diſſolved, that they did juſtly ſuſpect that the authours thereof were no ſmall offenders and much they doubted that their gracious Soveraigne had not beene rightly enformed of their humble, hearty, and loyall intentions towards him, the dignity of his Crowne, ſafety of his perſon, peace, and welfare of his Common-wealth. Many other complaints ſhe heard, and grieved to heare, what is not fit to be ſo publikely related; briefly, there was mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring in all ſorts, diſcontent at all ſides, and ſadneſſe in all countenances, ſo that the amazed <hi>Albania</hi> upon view there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of was terribly taken with a trembling in all parts of her, ſo that her members ſeemed diſ-joynted, and ready to fall aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, the paine encreaſing towards her heart made her looke pale, and withall ſhe became ſo faint, that, no longer able to ſupport her weake limbes, ſhe fell downe, and lay without motion, as one dead, or entranced with ſome extreame paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, but long in this agony had ſhe not continued, when the two Ladies, <hi>Agape,</hi> and <hi>Sympathia</hi> came happily to her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe, taking her into their armes, and carrying her into the next lodging, they gently laid her on a bed; And now the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:125649:12"/>
report, for ill newes hath large wings, being ſpread farre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, Phyſitians, like vapours exhaled by the ſunne, repaire to her from all parts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Porters, Peaſants, and Horſe-groomes, give their opinions; Markets, Innes, Tavernes, Barbers ſhops and Bake-houſes, have their councell Tables; Women, and old Wives tell their tales, and preſcribe remedies: but of all the reſt, there were three notable Impoſtors, that tooke the cure on them, and that was <hi>Empericus</hi> a quackeſalver, one that ſtood much upon experience, and knew effects onely, without conſideration of their cauſes, a man that was skil'd more in the termes than the Art of his Profeſſion, and was of ſuch a plaufible tongue, that by his flatteries he could ſcrue, and inſinuate himſelfe into the affection of his Patient; his phyſicke conſiſted moſt in oyles and plaiſters, that would draw a skinne over the griefe, and make a faire ſhew to the eye, whiles it feſtered inwardly, and grew worſe. The ſecond was <hi>Chymicus,</hi> a Paracelſian, that had diſtilled the little braine he had in his Lymbecke of folly together with his other met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, whiles he built Caſtles in the aire, and blowed away his owne and other mens ſilver, that he might be a begger in purſe and rich in conceit: His Recipes were all compounded of new projects and inventions, and the drugges he gave were ſo loathſome, and ineffectuall, that the ſicke were forced to vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them up againe, and his Chryſopoſis and Antidotes were like himſelfe, of no vertue, and worth nothing. The laſt was <hi>Philargyros,</hi> a covetous Mountebanke, whoſe love was more to his Fee, then knowledge or care was for his Patient. This blood-ſucker was all in the drawing veine, ſo that with the Horſe-leaches, and Cupping-glaſſes, he applyed to ſuch parts as had more need of ſupply then abatement, he ſo weakened the reſt, that he put all in danger. Such were the Phyſitians, and by them you might conceive more feare of harme, than hope of remedy, and ſo it proved; for theſe fellowes, after much adoe to little purpoſe, ſeeing by all ſymptomes that their medicines did worke quite contrary effects, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what courſe next to take, give over, and leave the Patient in worſe caſe then they found her, and as they thought, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperately incurable; for as yet <hi>Albania</hi> was without ſenſe of her malady, or remembrance of their cauſe: which the good old <hi>Chronos</hi> perceiving, and much pitying, as one that had
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:125649:12"/>
beene a conſtant friend to her for many yeares, had ſeene much in his time, and had overpaſſed many alterations in himſelfe and others, poſts away (for though he was aged, he was not ſlow paced) to a ſolitary grove in a remote Land, wherein was a cave ſo deepe and obſcure, that it was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes night there, but he that was wont to travaile no leſſe in the greateſt darkeneſſe than at mid-day, enters undaunted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and returnes with the faire <hi>Alitheia</hi> in his hand, whom he brings to ſee the light, and ſhe (naked though ſhe was) is not aſhamed to be ſeene; to her he declares in what caſe he had left <hi>Albania,</hi> and the cauſe of his comming. <hi>Alitheia</hi> ſoone conceived, what in truth before ſhe feared, when ſhe laſt ſaw her, and therefore was much grieved at her departure ſo to leave her, but ſeeing the leaſt delay was very dangerous, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtulating no farther with the old man about cirdumſtances, ſhe called to her an old ſervant of hers, named <hi>Veridicus,</hi> whom (intending with all ſpeed, according as ſhe heard or ſaw oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, to follow after) ſhe ſent with <hi>Chronos,</hi> having given him ſufficient inſtructions what to doe; <hi>Veridicus</hi> was (as his name ſpake him) an honeſt tell-troth, though plaine, yet bold, and though forward, yet reſpectfull, and he was ſo well skild in his Art, and ſo confident of his undertakings, that if his preſcriptions were carefully obſerved, he doubted not of ſuch ſucceſſe as might be juſtly expected; and in this hope his ability and charity preſſing him onward, he ſoone arrives with <hi>Chronos</hi> in a happy ſeaſon, at the lodging where the ſicke Lady was; <hi>Veridicus</hi> ſtaid and knockt at the gate, <hi>Chronos</hi> paſt on, (as his manner was) when forth comes <hi>Philauta</hi> a ſtate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dame, and opens, but caſting her eye upon <hi>Veridicus,</hi> and ſeeing him in ſuch homely array, judging of the perſon by the attire, ſhe diſdainefully, without ſpeaking a word, or ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what he would, retires her ſelfe, and ſhut faſt the gate af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: but <hi>Veridicus</hi> nothing diſmaid with this affront well un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding from what ſubject it proceeded, knockes againe, and with more earneſtneſſe, (ſuch are the times for pooreſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters) till that <hi>Novata,</hi> another of <hi>Albania's</hi> attendants, more deſirous of novelties, than fearefull of her Miſtreſſes diſturban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, lets him in without further queſtion, and then under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the cauſe of his comming, whether for to ſatisfie her curioſity, or becauſe her Miſtreſſe was forſaken of all others,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:125649:13"/>
in this deſperate eſtate ſhe uſhers him to her preſence, who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently without more complement or regard of the ſtanders by, takes their ſicke Lady by the hand, feeles the pulſe, which ſometimes was very ſlow in motion, and then preſently as violent in agitation; he takes the Urinall, viewes her ſtate, findes it to be of a very high ſanguine colour, and much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled; he lookes on her viſage, beholds it wan and gaſtly; he would have asked her ſome queſtions, but ſhe could not anſwer for want of the uſe of her ſenſes, beſides that, her tongue was all blacke and ſwolne, the which and other like ſymptomes, argued the patient to be in a dangerous diſtemper in all parts of her body: And hereby he further perceived, that the two prime ſenſes of ſight and hearing, were ſo ill affected in their inſtrumentall nerves, that all objects ſeemed to exceed or leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen from their due proportion in quantity and quality, ſo that diſcords were taken for uniſons, and apparences, for ture ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, and ſo on the contrary; and being in this manner preſented to the common ſenſe, were likewiſe delivered over to the phantaſy, which by reaſon of divers fumes, ingendred in that cell of the braine, cauſed the like error in the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and memory, and by reaſon of the ill affection of theſe ſuperiour intelligible faculties, he found the inferiour, and more ſenſitive parts to partak and be oppreſſed with their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular maladies, as the heart to be much paſſionated with the diſſimulations and waverings of <hi>Liliana,</hi> the Lungs to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed, and breath faintly through the hot and biting di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtillations of <hi>Idolana,</hi> the ſtomacke to be overcharged with the gluttony and ſurfettings of <hi>Aquilina,</hi> the belly tympani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed with the windy vapours of <hi>Glorioſa,</hi> the Loynes impoſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matized with the inflammations of luſtfull <hi>Zelotypia,</hi> the hands bliſtered with the itchings of <hi>Argyria,</hi> her legges and feet la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and ſwolne with the gout of <hi>Argoa,</hi> into which loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome eſtate ſhe was not ſo much fallen by meanes of native conſtitution or complection, but through infection of the humours, by the corruption of the times, imitation, and too familiar converſe with her Neighbours, the negligence and ignorance of covetous attendants, ill Counſellors, and unskilfull Phyſitians: ſo that <hi>Veridicus</hi> conſidering her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorable eſtate, much grieved thereat, and could not but ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptly in ſome ſhort and paſſionate expoſtulation, thus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:125649:13"/>
it. Oh <hi>Albania!</hi> diſtreſſed and pittifull <hi>Albania,</hi> and the more (ſaid he) to be pittyed in thy diſtreſſe, becauſe <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bania!</hi> There is no time now to thinke on <hi>Megala,</hi> thy owne miſery is too much to thinke upon, happy hadſt thou beene, if thou couldſt ſooner have thought thy ſelfe unhappy; hadſt thou beene ſenſible of thy inward corraſives, as thou wert o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verjoyed with thy outward felicities, thy ſore had not thus growne to an ulcer, nor the pricke brought thee in danger of the Gangrene; thy too much overweening in proſperity, hath humbled thee to this grievous adverſity, thy too much mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying thy owne power, and excellencies above thy Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hours, hath now dejected thee to their contempt, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies; thy exalting thy ſelfe in compariſon of all others, hath almoſt made thee unworthy the compariſion for any. But I will not adde reproach to miſery. The occaſion and cauſe require rather helpe to draw thee out of the danger thou art unworthily brought into, then enquiry by what meanes thou wert brought into the danger: Both ſince the time is ſhort, and the diſeaſe ſharpe, the cure muſt be as quicke, and the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine of the greater vertue and operation, which the more it ſmarts, the ſooner will heale. Have but the patience to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure, you ſhall the ſooner finde eaſe, and but pardon the rudeneſſe of the Phyſitian, and let me not be miſtaken in the ſincerity of my endeavours, you ſhall ſoone perceive, that in the leaſt flattery is moſt friendſhip, and although a ſweet bit doth beſt pleaſe a curious pallat, yet that a bitter pill is more profitable, and that plaine dealing hath no fellow.</p>
            <p>Having thus ſaid, he againe tooke her by the hand, and bid her be of good cheare, but perceiving that ſhe was inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of what he ſpake or did, he ſaw it was high time from the apparent cauſe, to bethinke himſelfe of the convenient cure; and that firſt of all it was neceſſary to uſe the next meanes for reſtoring her to the uſe of her ſenſes, that ſhe might come to ſome feeling of that deplorable eſtate ſhe was then in. To which purpoſe he ſpouts into her noſtrils that pretious wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Mnemoſyne,</hi> with which the obſtacles of her memory were ſoone cleared, and the paſſages of her eares unſtopped, ſo that ſhe might truely diſtinguiſh the ſounds which ſhe heard; and to her eyes he applyed a <hi>Gnoſticke Collyrium,</hi> by vertue whereof all miſts vaniſhed from her ſight, ſo that ſhe could
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:125649:14"/>
plainely diſcerne objects preſented to them, as they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, and not as they ſeemed to be: Then in a potion (as well as he could) he gave her a Cordiall of ſincerity for the heart, a cleaning Electuary of integrity for the Lungs, a dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et drinke of temperance for the Stomacke, a purge of humble dejections for the belly, a cooling oyntment of continence for the Loynes, a pleaſing ſalve of contentment for the hands, and a quicke-working plaiſter of Action for the Legges and Feete; and ſo to each other Malady, he proportioned a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per medicine: and now that he might further know her mind by her ſpeech, with a ſoveraigne water, which <hi>Alitheia,</hi> had given him, and he knew to be effectuall for that purpoſe, he waſhed her tongue, and preſently ſhe perceiving, that hereby ſhe recovered free ability of ſpeech, neglecting to take notice of any that ſtood about her, in a moſt pitifull manner, caſting her eyes towards Heaven (a hopefull ſigne of a perfect reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very to enſue) often lifting up her hands, and then preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with them ſmiting her breſt, ſhe ſignifyed in the one, the heartineſſe of her gratulatory and manifeſted her true Repentance, and the ſorrowfull compunctions of her heart; by the other whiles ſighing, and all the whiles bitterly ſobbing (the teares trickling downe her cheekes in great a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance) the firſt words ſhe ſpake were, <hi>O Ens Entium mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerere mei!</hi> and then turning to <hi>Veridicus</hi> in all kinde and thankefull manner, acknowledged the benefit ſhe had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from him, and promiſed a future mindfullneſſe, and ſhe requeſted him upon his former care, not yet to leave her in that caſe, for feare of a relapſe, and for what courſe was far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be uſed for perfecting of the cure, ſhe relyed upon his care, and would be ruled by his adviſe: ſhe bemoaned her great ingratitude towards her Omnipotent Benefactor, and preſerver, whom for his many and extraordinary bleſſings, ſhe had requited with multitude of deepe unkindneſſrs and tranſgreſſions: ſhe bewailed her over-great neglect of the forlorne <hi>Megala,</hi> and over-much credit, and reſpect of her cruell and treacherous enemy, forraine and domeſticke, and therefore judged her ſelfe worthily rewarded, in ſeeing the diſtractions of her owne Country; But whiles ſhe was thus bemoaning her many calamities, the noyſe of drummes and trumpets that ſounded over all the Country, came to her eares
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:125649:14"/>
whereby ſhe was ſtricken with a new terrour of fearing ſome danger towards, by reaſon of the precedent evils; but upon demanding the cauſe, when newes was brought her, that her ſiſter <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nita</hi> was proclaimed a rebell, ſhe could not forbeare to cry out, wringing her hands, tearing her haire with other like extreame paſſion of dolour, and impatience, till that the prudent <hi>Viridicus</hi> was conſtrained to uſe force with entreaties to bring her to reaſon, and he could not but ſharpely reprove her weakeneſſe, that ſhe would play the Childe, and be ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of others harme, whiles ſhe was not yet cured of her owne, and that it was above his Art to effect what onely lay in the power and will of her Prince to doe: and therefore he muſt be ſued unto, or elſe what he could adviſe would be to ſmall effect, onely his endeavour ſhould never be wanting, and what wanted of power in him to this effect, ſhould be ſupply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the greater willingneſſe.</p>
            <p>Now the truth is, that <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nita</hi> upon the report of <hi>Albaniaes</hi> ſickneſſe and her owne diſcontents, under colour of a viſit contrary to the will and command of her Soveraigne (as was ſuppoſed) had with troopes of her Countrymen, marched beyond her limits, and made way by force of Armes, into the territories of her Neighbours, and committed Acts which in their firſt appearance ſavoured of ſome diſobedience, and gave ſuſpition of ill intents, not onely towards <hi>Albania,</hi> but to the Soveraigne of both Kingdomes; and although their promiſes and proteſtations pretend the contrary, and argue mainely for the juſtneſſe of ſuch an entry, and though (to ſpeake charitably) we beleeve their mindes to accord with their words, I cannot ſee how actions of this nature can be juſtifyable, except you will allow extraordinary effects, to extraordinary occaſions; In conſideration whereof <hi>Albania</hi> was ſo diſmaid with her ſiſters preſumption and overſight in offending her Lord and Maſter, laying her ſelfe open to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt contempt, and hazarding the ſafety of her King and Religion (as ſhe then ſuppoſed by this indiſcreet attempt) and hereupon, but more eſpecially in regard of her owne e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, ſhe entreated <hi>Veridicus</hi> (as he had before adviſed) that he would ſpeedily ſupplicate her gracious Soveraigne, in her behalfe, to give way that ſuch courſe might be ſpeedily taken for the redreſſe of the evils hapned to her, and her ſiſter <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nita;</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:125649:15"/>
as had beene alwayes ſucceſſefully uſed by his Majeſties pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors, for the preventing and aboliſhing like miſchiefes: for otherwiſe there would be ſmall hopes of her abſolute re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, and if ſhe did miſcarry, his Majeſty could not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe himſelfe ſecure ſafety, upon any ground that did yet ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Veridicus,</hi> as well to content the diſconſolate Lady, as to diſcharge his owne duty, which bound him to expoſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to any travaile or danger for the ſervice of his Prince and Country, takes the charge upon him, and without delay, weighing the danger of relapſe in <hi>Albania,</hi> and miſtruſting the purpoſes of diſcontented <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nita,</hi> prepares for the Court, from which, pity it is, he had beene ſo long abſent.</p>
            <p>But at his departure he wiſheth <hi>Albania</hi> to diſmiſſe ſome of her old attendants, and commended unto her two of her La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies kinſwomen, <hi>Agatha</hi> and <hi>Fidelia,</hi> to be neare unto her, and of her Councell, for they had beene brought up from their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy with <hi>Aletheia,</hi> and had learned of her how to ſpeake and behave themſelves, and ſo carrying themſelves according to her inſtructions, all things have happily ſucceeded, which have beene committed to their truſt and managing. Farther he wiſhed her to be very wary and circumſpect with whom ſhe did treate, or participate her affaires, not to give the leaſt bearing to any ſpeech that reliſhed of flattery or vaine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, nor fix her eyes ſteadily for any time upon the faireſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> carnall objects the world could afford, nor give countenance to the project of any inſinuating Sycophant (under the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of private gaine) againſt the common good; never to murmure at her Soveraignes Prerogative, nor to queſtion his juſt commands, nor be unwilling to pay his lawfull impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions; not to utter any thing paſſionately againſt his Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, or their Commiſſion, but leave them to their competent Judges; and evermore to be frequent in her Oriſons to the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame governor of all Creatures, that he would turne all to the beſt, and ſo direct the heart of her Prince, that he would yeeld a gracious eare, and ſet a period to all her troubles: and for her owne eaſe, he wiſhed her to faſt often, and when ſhe was forced by the neceſſity of nature, to take ſome repaſt, ſhe ſhould be ſparing in her delicates, and eate not to the glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of her appetite, ſo that theſe ill humours, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:125649:15"/>
would abound, and iſſued from divers parts of her body, might be abated, and the whole better prepared for conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent phyſicke, to the recovery of her former health, without diſmembring any part of the ſame, if poſſibly it might be<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſo he left her expecting the Ladies, whom he had appointed to waite on her.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Veridicus</hi> was at the point to be gone, but bethinking him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe that the acceſſe to the King for ſo plaine and blunt a fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low as he was, (in a time of ſuch employment and affaires of ſo high conſequence, whereabouts the moſt Honourable and wiſeſt heads of the Kingdome were aſſembled, to conſult and determine; and that he ſhould come with a tale already told) would not be eaſily granted, nor was it fit yet, conſidering his promiſe, and that his Soveraigne would not diſdaine to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a petition from the meaneſt Subject, preſented in the way of due reſpect and loyalty, though he proceeded not in the journey, he preſumed to take pen and write his minde, in a few petitionary lines; and that they might be as graciouſly accepted, as they were dutifully endyted, he directed them to his ſacred Majeſty, by the hands of two vertuous and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Meſſengers, <hi>Sophia</hi> and <hi>Sophroſyna,</hi> to this effect.</p>
            <p>Moſt high and mighty Prince, as the eternall Majeſty doth not diſdaine to caſt downe an eye of favour upon the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſupplication of the Royall Potentates on Earth: ſo Princes that take this ſupreame Lord for their patterne, ſometimes thinke it no diſparagement, to reach out a gracious hand, and receive a petition from their meaneſt Subject. It is true, that your Majeſty is a Prince, for eminency in graces and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, farre above others of this high calling, and I am your Subject of the lower ranke, called <hi>Veridicus,</hi> that love to ſpeake the Truth: I have had my breeding in the Country, my ſpeech is as my ſelfe, plaine, and rude, without Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke or other Art. And therefore it may be judged too great preſumption, for a perſon of ſo meane degree and parts, to come ſo neare as the Chamber of ſuch Royall preſence; but knowing your Highneſſe to be good, as well as great, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving heard that your Majeſty, out of the gracious temper of your mild and vertuous diſpoſition, and inclination towards the content and welfare of all your loyall Subjects, of what degree ſoever, have granted free acceſſe and audience to their
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:125649:16"/>
juſt and reaſonable requeſts, it hath em boldned me (though the meaneſt) amongſt other (none being ſo bold as the blind Bayard) to addreſſe the deſires of your ſubject and Handmaid the dejected <hi>Albania,</hi> to your Princely conſideration, hoping that the uprightneſſe of mind ſhall excuſe the rudeneſſe of the delivery, and that the honeſty of the matter ſhall begge par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for the meſſenger, and where duty is intended, no miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtruction ſhall have place, whiles I ſtrive to be briefe, that I be not offenſive.</p>
            <p>It is not unknowne to your ſacred Majeſty (ill fame hath a ſwift pace) how that <hi>Albania</hi> of late hath beene ſurprized with ſo ſtrange and unuſuall maladies, that her beſt Doctors are almoſt at their wits end, and know not what to make of the cauſe or cure, except your Majeſty give leave that the free practiſe of the skillfull, according to the patterne of former times, be ſpeedily put in execution, for ſearching into the roote, and drawing forth the ill humours, that have beene the meanes, and are the maintenance of her diſtempered e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Albania,</hi> your poore diſtreſſed ſupplicant, is not ſo much caſt downe with the conſideration of her preſent miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, as with the griefe ſhe conceives of your Highneſſe diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure towards her, for the neglect of duty and ill ſervices, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſhe knowing her ſelfe as guiltleſſe in her indeavours, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, as her accuſers are malicious, and groundleſſe in their purpoſes, humbly beſeecheth that ſhe be not condemned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe be heard, and that her cauſe may be freely pleaded be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your Majeſty, in that high Court of the generall Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, and diſcuſſed in all points fully to the end, without her adverſaries interruption or diſturbance.</p>
            <p>No Subjects of any Prince (I ſpeake confidently, what I know to be true) ever more heartily loved their Soveraigne, or more deſired his Honour and ſafety, than Yours: Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe how glad, when there was but mention of a Parliament, wherein they might ſhew ſome reall expreſſions of their wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſſe; then how caſt downe were they, when it was ſo ſuddenly diſſolved, and they miſtaken; but ſince it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed your gracious Majeſty, out of your wiſdome, and innate clemency, according to the example of your moſt Worthy Predeceſſors, willingly to give a happy beginning, and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:125649:16"/>
promiſes of a faire continuance to another Aſſembly, upon the earneſt requeſt of your Worthy Nobles, and the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall deſire of your true hearted Commons, both for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medying of all former miſconceites, and prevention of future diſcontents, and inconveniencies, with what an unanimous acclamation of joy, vowes, wiſhes, hath it beene received? The Almighty grant, that no factious or ill-minded ſpirit to the generall good, may ſtop or breake off the lawfull proceedings therein.</p>
            <p>And now, as formerly, the hope and deſire of all true hearts is, that the Truth of Religion may be ſupported, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, and whatſoever makes not with it, or is againſt it, (how pretious ſoever it be in ſhew) may be taken away; Your Majeſty hath piouſly given your word already, and ſhewby your daily practiſe, how your affection ſtands enclined, and it is nothing doubted of your part, of a firme continuance, but becauſe no good thing can be made too ſure, and for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of ſucceeding times, it may not be impertinent to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme it by ſome new Act, in ſuch manner as by this Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Aſſembly, with your Majeſties approbation, ſhall be thought to ſort moſt with the glory of God, and the purity of the primitive inſtitutions; next to the honour of God, and removing of the preſent grievances, a confirmation of the juſt Lawes and Liberties of the Kingdome is deſired, and in this requeſt, that the welfare and Honour of your Majeſty is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, may be eaſily proved, as alſo that thoſe of your Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, which ſtand up ſo ſtoutly for their lawes and liberties (ſo warrantable as they are) are not the worſt welwillers to the dignity of the Crowne, whiles they ſeeke not ſo much their owne advantages herein, as thoſe which are contrary minded are found to doe, but declare themſelves impartiall in their deſignes, and that as faſt and faithfull vaſſalles, not to be carryed with the change of time or fortunes, as ill counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors, whoſe projects, though at the firſt ſight ſeeme to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe much, yet in the iſſue doe faile commonly. I ſuppoſe your Majeſty would not deſire to be King of ſuch a baſe and ſlaviſh-minded people, as were careleſſe obſervers, or wilfull neglecters of thoſe juſt Ordinances and Priviledges, under which the Kingdome hath beene ſo long time happy and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous: for as thoſe Princes are accounted Tyrants, that rule
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:125649:17"/>
onely by compulſion of the Subjects againſt the Lawes, ſo may thoſe Subjects be eſteemed no better than Aſſes that beare any burthen is laid upon their backes, it is much to be ſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that ſuch as love innovations, and attempt change of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernement, may by the ſame reaſon be drawne in time to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like of the Governors themſelves. When we are in a good and ſure way, it is ſafe keeping in it, for thoſe by-pathes which we conceive to be nearer, are hard to finde, and more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous; and the policy is neither commendable nor profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, to learne the hurt of ill counſell by experience. Now the way to maintaine the Kings Prerogative, (the greateſt Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative of a King, is the preſerving of his Juſtice) and to keepe on foot the Liberties of his Subjects, is by that gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Councell (as now by your Majeſties gracious favour hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily met together) of the whole Land preſented in ſome particulars for that end, and that this hath beene the readieſt way of providing convenient ſupplies for the Princes occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and neceſſities, for redreſſing the Countries grievances, and puniſhments of capitall Offenders; neither can there be any other meanes deviſed, whereby to levy greater ſummes of money for the Kings uſe more ſpeedily, or with like cheare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullneſſe, and in ſuch manner, that no perſon ſhall have juſt cauſe to complaine, or be ſo impoveriſhed, but upon another occaſion ſhall be able and willing to give againe, whereas (whatſoever others project or perſwade to the contrary) taxes and impoſitions enforced on the Subject in an extraordinary manner, and way, are (experience too well ſheweth it) un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingly, and but in part, with a great deale of murmur and grudging from thoſe which are leaſt able to beare extorted. For there is not the leaſt Worme, but being trodden upon will turne taile, though he may not, nor dare make reſiſtance; and every man in a common tumult will ſeeke to ſhift his Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, and the weaker muſt of neceſſity goe to the Wall, and men (when they are driven to extremities) will be ſwayed more by paſſion then reaſon, and there is hard reclaming of affection by force, when it is once alienated. Whereupon the common ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my taking, or making occaſions, will caſt in his hooke, and fiſh in thoſe troubled waters: all which this general Aſſembly may happily prevent, whereby the heart of the Prince and peopleu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited in the adamantine linkes of reciprocall affection, things
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:125649:17"/>
hereafter will goe on in ſo faire and loving manner, that each part ſhall hold it ſelfe well ſatisfied, and no privie traytor, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen adverſary whatſoever dare to practiſe againſt ſuch combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned forces. And this, moſt excellent Prince, is the main end that drawes all true hearts upon their knees, to beg of your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that as you have honored this Aſſembly of your ſubjects with a happie beginning, and profer of much favour, by the encouragement of your gracious preſence, and promiſes; ſo you would be pleaſed (notwithſtanding the importunities of any oppoſition) to give it the rights appertaining to the ſame, and ſuffer it to have ſuch a peaceable progreſſe, that your ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject may be able to expreſſe the true intention of his deſire, and manifeſt the ſincere affection of his heart, in willingly perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming what ſhall moſt ſtand with your Majeſties Honour, and ſafety of the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>But if under the pretext of loyalty (which cannot be imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in hearts of ſuch unſtained Religion) there were harbou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in any of this Aſſembly a deſire to bring innovations into Church or Commonwealth, if they did ſeeke to derogate any thing from your Majeſties honour, or juſt prerogative, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance their owne liberties by exemptions from their ancient dues, or to bring in, or allow of any other kind of governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and authority, Civill, or Eccleſiaſticall, that might counterchecke, or diminiſh from the Royall dignity of the Crowne; if they did ſeeke to monopolize any commodity for their particular advantage, had any project that did ayme at any private end, and not concurre with the good of the generall State; if their grievances were fained, or preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, which they could not manifeſtly prove, or were not too ſenſible of, could they pitch upon any other courſe or way, whereby your Majeſties deſires might be ſatisfied, wants ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, and their grievances eaſed, neither the ſorrowfull <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bania,</hi> true meaning <hi>Veridicus,</hi> or any other ſubject, that had the leaſt ſparke of reaſon, or were well in his wits, would at this time inſiſt in any needleſſe, and unjuſt petition, to ſo Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Majeſty, and rejoyce to have induced the meanes of his Countries miſery, together with the certaine ruine of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and his poſterity.</p>
            <p>But when is ſhall be proved to be otherwiſe, how much are they in blame, and what enemies to the State (I would ſad
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:125649:18"/>
experience did not witneſſe it) which imputing the fault where is none, have beene the hinderance of the proceedings, and cauſes of the late diſſolutions of this Aſſembly, whereby their actions might not be brought in queſtion (a child may tumble a ſtone into a well, which a multitude of ſtrong men ſhall hardly be able to draw out) and thereupon the opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of preventing the dangers, and expences, which have ſince followed, have beene omitted with other inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſo faſt comming on, that your Majeſty is, as it were, now enforced upon this courſe, in much ſtrictneſſe of time, and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulencie of buſineſſe, that the wiſeſt under ſtandings tremble to thinke what will be the iſſue, if this aſſembly have no better ſucceſſe than formerly: In the meane while, if ſuch mean well as are ſuſpected of this notorious injury done to their King &amp; State (I can accuſe none; but ſure there cannot be ſmoake without fire) mee thinkes they of all other ſhould deſire the tryall of a Parliament, that ſo they may be cleared from theſe foule aſperſions, and their innocence manifeſted by a more ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall vote, and their accuſers cenſured; and upon this ground was that worthy reſolution of <hi>Leoniſſa</hi> obſervable, that if any man complained unjuſtly againſt a Magiſtrate, it were reaſon he ſhould be ſeverely puniſhed; if juſtly, ſhe was Queene of the ſmall, as well as of the great: and hereby alſo ſhall the true authors be the ſooner diſcouraged; and for example, receive their condigne puniſhment, who although in way of excuſe, may pretend your Highneſſe allowance for their doings, yet while they principally ſought the accompliſhment of their owne deſignes, with the diſhonour of their Prince, and thoſe (it is a mixime in Policie) that reſpect not their Princes ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, cannot be well ſaid to love his perſon, their actions can no way be juſtifiable, ſince thoſe favourites that turn Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates to due obedience, and abuſe a favour afforded to them, to the injury of the Giver, do too much undervalue their Prince, and are of all ungratefull perſons the worſt, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the higheſt of puniſhments. And by the diſcovery of theſe offenders your Majeſty ſhall reape a double benefit. Firſt, a freedome from ill counſell, and practiſes, with the gaine of ſounder hearts and adviſes. Secondly, a reunion of your ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects hearts and affections: to which for your Majeſties ſafety, the deviſes of all the Projectors in the world are nothing
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:125649:18"/>
comparable; and in this regard the deſire of a learned, &amp; valiant Prince in his time was no leſſe truly royall, than memorable, in that hee had rather be maſter of his ſubjects hearts, than their goods; and Lord of their affections, rather than a Conquerour of his enemies dominions: and beſides this, your Majeſty ſhall aſſure all doubting ſpirits, that you are more led in your reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions by judgement than paſſion: and that you can make uſe of ill inſtruments no farther than to worke out good ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects by them: that your favour is ſwayed according to deſert, that your deeds ſhall be effectuall, as your promiſe hath been gracious, and hereby their groſſe ſtupidity, to the diſpiriting, and terrour of other like as thought to manage all the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of the State with ſuch an high, and abſolute hand, and in the meane time to dance in a net, undeſcryed, unpuniſhed, ſhall more plainly appeare, and the difference will be made evident betwixt ſuch as counſell for their owne ends, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, and others that do it meerly out of duty, without other reſpects. Now what farther benefit will accrue to the Kingdome by demonſtration of your Majeſties regard to the love and deſires of your peoples requeſt, and how your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe prerogative can be no wayes abridged, your Exchequer more plentifully furniſhed, your honourable intentions ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to your owne expectation accompliſhed, your friends and well-wiſhers comforted, your enemies, domeſtique, and forraine diſcouraged, time will ſhortly bring to light with moſt infallible evidences.</p>
            <p>But I feare in ſo farre preſſing my meſſage, I have forgot to whom I ſpeake, and the perſon I was to repreſent, the diſtreſſe of <hi>Albania</hi> (dread Soveraigne) hath cauſed this exceſſe of ſpeech, wherein if I have beene impertinent in any extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gances, or too tedious with needleſſe tautologies, I hope your Majeſty will gratiouſly pardon theſe errours of love &amp; duty, and your humble vaſſall ſhall ever pray for the proſperity of your long and peaceable Raigne on earth, the enjoyment and felicity of an endleſſe Raigne in Heaven: both which hee that is onely able, the Lord Almighty, for his Sonnes ſake graunt unto you for his Glory, the Churches good, and your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties eternall comfort.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Veridieus</hi> having in this free manner delivered the deſires of <hi>Albania</hi> to her Soveraigne, thought ſhe would not be ſatisfied,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:125649:19"/>
except her ſiſter <hi>Vnita,</hi> were ſomewhat expoſtulated with by him, concerning her arrivall at this time, and in ſuch manner: but underſtanding her deſire was not to treat with, or deliver the intentions of her mind to any but the generall aſſembly, he ſaw his labour would be needleſſe; yet howſoever, whiles he had pen and paper at hand, he wrote to her, and her aſſociates briefly and plainly to this effect.</p>
            <p>Unconquered <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nita,</hi> and yee my brethren of the North (for ſo I may now preſume to call you) what a joy to all true hearts is it to find, that the report of ſiniſter affections to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the common good is found a lier; and that your inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are hit herto juſtified by your loyalty, and fidelity to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the ſafety of your Prince, and the welfare of both Kingdomes? the enemies whereof, as they have ſhewed their ſelves malicious, ſo much more treacherous in their deſignes, than they could with all their inventions impute to others by any of their forged calumniations. Good Lord! what a plot of miſchiefe had they hammered out upon the anvill of their ſubtile deviſes to make us to miſunderſtand, and miſconſtrue each others words and actions? ſo that if the never failing mercy of God had not in the very moment of danger inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed it ſelſe to the preventing of what was intended, wee had barbarouſly ſheathed our ſwords in each others boſomes, and bathed them in the blood of our neareſt friends, to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable griefe of <hi>Verana,</hi> and long expected joy of <hi>Idolana.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alas it was farre from the thought of <hi>Albania,</hi> ever to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that her ſiſter <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nita</hi> would preſume to come neere the preſence of her Soveraigne with a petition in one hand, and a ſword in the other, without the extreme neceſſity of his Majeſty, and his Kingdomes good enforcing it: neither could ſhee beleeve that <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nita</hi> ſought to have the perſon of their joynt Liege under her abſolute power, that his word might be wholly at her command: neither could ſhee endure to heare with patience, that ſhee would prove ſo unjuſt, as to covet ſome place of abode for her greater eaſe in her ſiſters poſſeſſions: but ſhe is yet confident, and alwayes hath beene of the mind, that whereas ſhee hath ſurpriſed Townes and Caſtles, forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied them with ſtrong defences, it is more for the ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of her retreat in ſafety, than for any enjoyment after her juſt deſires are ſatisfied: neither can <hi>Albania</hi> any wayes blame
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:125649:19"/>
her demand of reparations for the wrongs and injuries ſhee hath ſuſtained, againſt thoſe that have beene the maine cauſe thereof, as being now diſcovered to be the ſole incentives of all the troubles in Church and Common-wealth, that have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happily of late, fallen out to the diſturbance of the bleſſed Iland in both Kingdomes; How faine would they have cauſed the abuſed parties to faſten upon this beleefe, that <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nita</hi> by taking up armes, and comming in this warlike manner (ſince by their cruell plots there was no other way left open for admittance) had manifeſted an open rebellion againſt her Prince? whiles the event hath hitherto publiſhed, that her prime accuſers have beene the great offenders, by whoſe wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked contrivances, both <hi>Albania</hi> &amp; <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nita</hi> were for a time hood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winked; and by a way, which they leaſt ſuſpected or dreamed, alike endangered to have falne headlong into an inevitable ruine of life, eſtate, religion, and all together.</p>
            <p>A cunning devill, thus to turne Angell of light, and under the colour of religion and juſtice, politiquely to undermine the ſtate of the Church, and the liberty of the ſubject, by its owne meanes, and inſtruments, to betray the Court with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuations of new projects, to defile the Temple with ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious ceremonies, and the pulpit with new doctrines, and ſtrange opinions, to breed jealouſies betwixt a moſt loving Prince, and his loyall people, by breach of Parliaments, and perverting of juſtice: and having thus put all things into a generall confuſion (like the fiſh <hi>Sepia</hi> that blackes the water to blind the fiſherman) to thinke to eſcape undiſcerned, una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided: But thankes to the Almighty, through his provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence the net is broken, and wee are delivered; it is through his great mercy, and not our foreſight, that the common ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my (who ſtood waiting when the mine for our deſtruction would be fired, that hee might have blowne the coales to maintaine the flames of a miſconceived diviſion) cannot yet by any ſecret or open ſtratagem of his, take advantage to do that harme he would, and hath long wiſhed.</p>
            <p>Had the imagination of theſe wrongs to <hi>Albania</hi> beene grounded upon meere ſuſpitions, and no certaine evidences, and lamentable experiences: or had there beene cauſe to miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſt ſo much injuſtice and ambition in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nita,</hi> under the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text of right, to promote ſome private ends, could any man
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:125649:20"/>
be ſo partiall in his judgement, or ſenſleſſe to thinke that the one would have taken up ſuch bitter complaints, or the other thought to have wrought out her purpoſes by force of arms, and open violence againſt her ſiſter (beſides her other ſtrength) aſſiſted with a right cauſe, and ſo powerfull a Soveraigne; and ſuppoſe ſhee might conteſt ſo farre with her in an unjuſt way, as to gaine a victory or two upon great advantages, (the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine jnſtice for our ſinnes permitting her to take ſuch a foyle) yet <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nita</hi> could not be ſo ignorant in the meane while, as not to conceive her owne extreme danger in one overthrow, which in this cauſe were moſt likely to fall out, and that in the upſhot it had beene farre better (it was well thought upon by an experienced Captaine of his time) never to have fought, than thus to overcome; when beſides the rebelling againſt her Soveraigne, the wronging her deareſt friends, to the infamy of her name, there muſt needs have followed the overthrow of her eſtate, life, and liberty, with an expoſing of her poſterity, friends, and religion it ſelfe, to the mercy of the common ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary, with the generall dammage to all the reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in <hi>Verana.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore truly they muſt be very malicious, and tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terouſly minded, that would go about to perſwade, and <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bania</hi> ſhould be very ſimple to be perſwaded of any ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, or purpoſes of her ſiſter thus towards her, who had ſhee profeſſed her ſelfe an enemy, had offered injuries and affronts beyond ſufferance (God forbid our ſinnes ſhould by any ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies practiſes come to that height, or that neighbours, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of one language, ſubjects of one Soveraigne, and profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of the ſame true religion, ſhould ſo much forget them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves) yet it cannot enter into my thoughts, that <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nita</hi> would preſently thruſt herſelfe into ſuch a courſe of revenge, as thereby to bring her Country to utter deſolation, and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, and ſubjugate her necke and liberties under the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of any forraine, or Idolatrous tyranny.</p>
            <p>But why mention I ſuch impoſſibilities? O blind ſpirited Idolaniſt, and Machiavilian politique, that loves ever to be making of troubled waters, and fiſhing in them, what old fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches are theſe of thine, out of the treaſury of thy Regicidian Fathers, and Counſellers, to raiſe jealouſies, breake amities, if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> might be, betwixt all relations, ſmother truths, palliate
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:125649:20"/>
falſhoods, to bring thy pernicious deſigns to thoſe effects (how prejudiciall ſoever) for which they were intended; but yet moſt fooliſh, unadviſed, and deſperate wretch, not to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand and learn, (by ſo many examples of the ſtrange diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and juſt puniſhment of treacherous intendments againſt Princes and Religion in all ages) the certaine miſery and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ruine thou throweſt thy ſelfe into, whiles God lookes on theſe thy actions with an eye of revenging juſtice, the Angels with diſdaine, the devill with laughter, and all good men with juſt indignation! Goe on thus to merit, thus to ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erogate; A traytors reward, will be alwayes a traytors con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comitant; like offences will require like puniſhments. I could never yet read, or heare of any traytors, but have beene recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penced with hatred by their chiefe abetters: ſome Princes may be ſo unjuſt as to love the treaſon which maketh for their ends, but none have beene ſo bad, either long to truſt or love the traytors: and what reaſon have they to eſteeme ſuch bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh and baſe ſpirited minds, as to attaine a little tranſitory ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour or pelfe, will venture their ſoules, life, wit, underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, goods, and what elſe they have, or hold deare, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray their Prince and Country, unto the cruelty of their anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and bloody minded enemy? O how much is every loyall heart diſtaſted with the thought of ſuch a miſchievous brood amongſt a people of ſo much civility, religion and unſtained nobility? Let <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nita</hi> pardon and beare with this paſſion to which my love and zeale for her welfare hath ſo farre tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſported mee.</p>
            <p>And (to conclude) my hope is that I am not deceived of her well-like wiſhings, and reall intentions of good towards <hi>Albania,</hi> for the ſtrengthning of their joynt forces againſt the common enemy, and inſeparable uniting of their hearts in a mutuall affection betwixt themſelves with a reſpectfull duty towards God, and their Prince, in the pureſt manner of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip towards the one, and dueſt kind of obedience towards the other: and therefore my deſire is, that both parties ſhould hereafter meete rather to imbrace than to ſtand in armes, much leſſe to fight each againſt other; but joyntly ſet upon their Soveraigne with the weapons of prayers and teares; but upon his enemies, and the enemies of his allies with the ſword and musket; and in the meane time to be importunate
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:125649:21"/>
with the Almighty, ſo to direct the heart of the King, and bleſſe the proceedings of the Parliaments in both Kingdomes, that all diſcontents, and grievances on each ſide be removed, God glorified, the King ſatisfied, the good Subject pleaſed, and the bad puniſhed, his enemies with thoſe of the ſword and musket: and our joynt deſire and expectation henceforth ſhall reſt in this, that God will ſo direct the heart of the King, and bleſſe the proceedings of this Honourable<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>Aſſembly, that all diſcontents, and grievances on each ſide, ſhall be happily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, and a time ſhortly follow for the manifeſt diſcovery, and juſt puniſhment of ſuch as have beene the diſturbers of the peace, and quiet of both the Kingdomes; and the Almighty preſerve us in this mind without faltring or diſſimulation to promote thoſe actions only which may tend to the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and encreaſe of his Glory, in all our counſels and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprizes.</p>
            <p>By this time <hi>Veridicus</hi> imagining hee had in ſome part diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged the office of a well-wiſher, and impartiall friend to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nita,</hi> and her well minded Country-men (howſoever by ſome malevolent ſpirits, it might be ſleighted, or not well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted) ſealed his letter, and ſent it away, by an old ſervant of his, named <hi>Plerophoros.</hi> And hereupon returning to ſee how it went with his languiſhing patient, and to acquaint her with what hee had done; in the way it was his chance to meet with <hi>Calopolites,</hi> an old acquaintance of his, and one that was cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen to be of the number of the generall Councell that was newly aſſembled in the behalfe of <hi>Albania,</hi> and ſome neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry occurrences that much concerned her, and her ſiſter <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nita,</hi> and therefore was ſo well imformed how the caſe ſtood be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them, that <hi>Veridicus</hi> needed not to make any new rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: to whom (though hee were in ſome haſt by reaſon of the weight and multitude of buſineſſe that did require pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence) the plaine old man imparted, what came into his his mind for the preſent, though briefly, yet with tokens of ſome zealous earneſtneſſe.</p>
            <p>O <hi>Calopolites,</hi> I know you to be underſtanding, and honeſt, (as your name imports) and that theſe two vertues are very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite for the charge you have undertaken, whereby you need not be inſtructed in what concernes your duty therein: yet give mee leave to expreſſe what is expected of your friends,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:125649:21"/>
and acquaintance, that you would be eſpecially mindfull of what ſhall tend to the benefit of the Church, and the Glory of God, firſt by carefully heeding to the ſecret plots, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minings of <hi>Idolana,</hi> for the excreaſe of Superſtition, and Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry: ſecondly, by timely ſuppreſſing that <hi>Luciferian</hi> pride of ſuch new Dogmatilts, as would intrude themſelves into the Eternall throne, and diſpute of the extent, and manner of the divine ſecrets by Election and Reprobation; and queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the equity of Gods Juſtice in its proceedings according to humane reaſon, by loving one and hating another before ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good or evill was committed by either of them; and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mure ſecretly, that his creatures are in his hands, as the clay in thoſe of the Potter, to make ſome veſſels of honour, others of diſhonour, according to his good will and pleaſure in all things. Moreover, they would have you to conſider how grievouſly <hi>Albania</hi> ſuffers in her Eſtate, by the extortion of the Uſurer, and griping officer, by pride in the exceſſe of apparell, by gluttony, and idleneſſe, through the multitude of Innes, Tavernes, and Gaming houſes: But I will not ſtay you longer with the inconveniences that grow from hence: you better can conceive of them, and apply fitting remedies: onely let me deſire you that ſince the beeſome is put into your hands by his Majeſties free bounty, that you would neglect no time, but be couragious (falſe fires and noyſes, are bug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beares onely to affright children) and having cleanſed the traſh that lies in open view upon the floore, you would ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacke every little corner of this great houſe, and ſweepe downe the ſpiders with their cob-webs of treachery and oppreſſion from each window therein, plucking downe the neſts of all ſwallow flatterers, from the top of ehe chimnies, and caſting all the filth out of doores, ſhut them ſo faſt, and locke them ſo ſure, that no falſe key may be able to give admittance here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after to any that would enter to defile theſe roomes againe.</p>
            <p>Thus ended <hi>Veridicus,</hi> and <hi>Calopolites</hi> promiſed to be mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of what he had ſaid, and ſo they lovingly parted, one to the Aſſembly, &amp; the other to <hi>Albania,</hi> whom at his comming he found walking in her chamber, and his Lady <hi>Aletheia</hi> with her two kinſwomen <hi>Agatha,</hi> and <hi>Fidelia</hi> in her company, by whom ſhee had beene much comforted. But when <hi>Veridicus</hi> (after due ſalutations to each of them) had acquainted her
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:125649:22"/>
with what was paſt, and of the hopefull proceedings in the Parliament, and the confideration of her cauſe, ſhee was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond meaſure cheered with the pleaſing newes.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Alethei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> the mean while was ſchooling <hi>Agnoa</hi> a ſimple ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced virgin, which in her journey towards <hi>Idolana</hi> (by good chance miſtaking the way) fell upon this place and company, and liked them ſo well, that ſhe had no mind, ſeeing the times begin to alter (ſo hot was her zeale) to travell farther, but deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to be entertained for ſome time in the houſe, and ſervice of <hi>Albania.</hi> But <hi>Agnoa,</hi> (ſaid the Lady) are you ſo taken up with this fond conceit, to find more holineſſe in <hi>Idolana,</hi> than in your owne Country? Do you thinke it any way commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable to take ſuch a long and dangerous journey, to kiſſe the foote of a proud Prelate (if that favour may be granted) and receive the benediction from a man of many infirmities? Silly girle! that canſt be perſwaded to call him thy Holy Father, who neither careth for God nor man: for he thruſts himſelfe into the ſeat of the one, and excommunicateth, and depoſeth the other, of what degree ſoever. If hee did feare God, he would not ſo derogate from his honour, and attribute ſo much to nature, Saints, Merits; Hee would not perſecute his ſervants under the name of Hereticks, for oppoſing his pride, and avarice, imputing ſuch errours of doctrine to them, as they neither acknowledge, but profeſſe the contrary, onely to colour his actions, and bring them into hatred with thoſe too credulous ignorants, whoſe beliefe is onely faſtened upon his elbowes. But what meanes it to ſay the <hi>Athanaſian</hi> Creed hath as much in it as is neceſſary to be beleeved, and yet to condenme thoſe of Hereſie, whoſe Creed with that of <hi>Athana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> is all one? But truly hee doth not ſo much oppoſe their tenets, as defend his owne errours. It is not ſo much for any untruth of that they beleeve, as that with their Articles of Faith, according to Gods Word, they receive not alike his traditions (additions) withall, that they are condemned for Heretickes. Now ſee the equity of the man, and hereby con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the holineſſe of your father, humble man, ſervant of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, with a triple Crowne, and Princes for his lackies, ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in all pompe, or carried upon mens ſhoulders. Chaſt Prieſt, making marriage a Sacrament, but holding it leſſe ſinne for a ſhaveling to lie with a concubine, than to wed a wife<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:125649:22"/>
What ſhould I mention the toleration, and yearly rent of his publique ſtewes, or of the continency of his Votaries, and how ſalacious in their Covents, witneſſe ſo many skulles, and reliques of murthered infants. Religious Votary, that haſt left the world for a cloyſter, and renounced the riches thereof to ſell Indulgences, graunt Diſpenſations, give Orders, and Titles, free ſoules out of a faigned Purgatory for meere chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, (for <hi>Omnia venalia Rome,</hi> was the ſaying of old) yea to allot ſo many yeares of pardon before the ſinnes are commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted! Temperate Saint, who counteſt it a true faſt to abſtaine from fleſh, and the meane while to feaſt, and ſurfet on greater delicates! Holy Maſſe-monger, that ſpeakeſt untruths in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne language to the ignorant people, who comming to ſee what is ſpoken, and as little underſtanding what they ſee, worſhip they know not what! But good Lord! what mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters doth hee make of thy Saints? How many heads, armes, legges, and other members have they to be worſhipped? how many garments? how many pieces of the holy Croſſe? how many nailes doth he ſuffer to be adored? what abundance of milke had the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> to be reſerved unto theſe times, for the encreaſe of <hi>Idolana<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> treaſury? what an extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry worke of piety for the Angels to tranſport her pallace from Jeruſalem to Loretto? Chriſtian policy, to get what huge ſums of money, by this or other lying Miracles: But how many Ladies are there? whilſt one hath her name from this Church, another from that? what ſtrange Saints doth the Pope make? (and he can canonize ſo many as hee pleaſeth) ſome of tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, ſome of ſuch as were perſecutors of good men, and ſome of ſhadowes, coyned in the <hi>Idea</hi> of his imagination, and well ſuſpected never to have beene more, than by the fabulous re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of fooliſh Legends, which are commonly repeated in the Sermons of the Fryers, to withdraw the memories, and minds of their hearers from the love of the ſacred Oracles. But to heare what blaſphemies, and abſurdities are contained there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, any modeſt eare would bluſh, and the Reader that made conſcience of truth, would be altogether aſhamed. But why ſtir I this filthy puddle? what doth not this pretended under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker to manage all things in heaven &amp; earth preſume? He can make of a creature a God, as of bread in the Sacrament of the Euchariſt by the vertue of Tranſubſtantiation: Hee can make
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:125649:23"/>
God as a creature, by turning the glory of God into the ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of a corruptible creature. This <hi>Agnoa</hi> is thy holy Father, ſo omnipotent, and ſo rare a wonder worker. And I am not ſo much aſhamed of thy groſſe ignorance (that may well be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the mother of ſuch devotion) but of great Potentates and worldly wiſe politicians (ſo well do carnall doctrines agree with great wealth, and projects) that love to be blindfolded, and ſtumble in the darke in ſuch a Sunſhine of the Goſpell, and light of the truth, as ſhines round about them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and yet they (as that ſilly old woman in <hi>Seneca,</hi> though ſhe were ſtark blind, would not be perſwaded that ſhee could ſee nothing was cauſed onely by the darkneſſe of the roome, and no defect of her eye-ſight) will make no queſtion but that they only are in the right, and will maintaine the infallibility of their ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme guider, and defend with tooth and naile, lies and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, treaſons and murders, by clipping of Orthodoxe truths with an <hi>Index expurgato<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ius,</hi> or harſh cenſure, and clapping in forged inventions, and manifeſt falſhoods into many of thoſe learned Authors workes, and treaſure them up in the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chives of their Babyloniſh <hi>Vatican<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> that (according to the beleefe, and after the manner of their forefathers) they as the true Catholiques of <hi>Verana,</hi> are onely within the pales of the Church, and that all ſuch as are otherwiſe minded are capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall heretiques, and worthy by ſword and fire to be rooted out from the face of the earth, and the ſociety of mankind. But thankes be to the Almighty that takes our part, ſo that (rage how they will) wee ſhall never be left wholly to their power, although for our ſinnes they may prove ſometimes (as the <hi>Canaanites</hi> to the children of Iſrael in thoſe times) thornes to our ſides<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> It ſhall be for a tryall to bring us to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and cauſe us to ſticke more neere unto our God, whom whilſt wee onely ſerve will againſt all enemies tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall or ſpirituall mightily defend us: but thoſe which in this manner ſtrive againſt him, are worthy in my judgement (I am not ſo uncharitable to have them drowned, and ſo to periſh body and ſoule) to be ſet up to the chin in the mad mans poole, till they come to ſee their folly, and be capable of ſome recovery: and thus <hi>Agnoa</hi> (ſaid thee) muſt you be dealt with, if you meane to ſtay here, or ſhortly reſolve to recant your er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours without delay, and declare your mind plainly without
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:125649:23"/>
any equivocation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or mentall reſervation. <hi>Agnoa,</hi> who was (as it ſeemes) of a very flexible diſpoſition, and ſomewhat ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie to be wrought upon, as having neither Sophiſtry, nor ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till diſtinctions, to ſet a faire colour upon a foule matter, nor impudencie flatly to deny, or contradict thoſe apparent truths, which <hi>Aletheia</hi> had delivered; and being out of the ſight, and adviſe of any <hi>Erra Pater,</hi> that might diſſwade her, promiſed to be ruled by their counſell.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Aſtene,</hi> one of <hi>Albania's</hi> faithfull ſervants, and that was very carefull of her Miſtreſſes welfare, and guilty of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo much (if tenderneſſe of conſcience in things indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent be an errour) as of too nice reſtraint of Chriſtian liberty, when ſhe ſaw that <hi>Agnoa,</hi> whoſe breeding and condition did ſo much differ from hers, was like to be admitted for a fellow ſervant, ſhe could not brooke it upon any termes, and was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout in a paſſionate way, to ſhew ſome tokens of her diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, but that <hi>Aletheia</hi> (who well knew her nature) perceiving, and much miſliking, by the way of prevention firſt began.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aſtene</hi> (ſaid ſhee) you need not be ſo much troubled (as by your countenance appeares) in that we have condeſcended to the requeſt of <hi>Agnoa,</hi> wherein wee do neither approve, nor meane to beare with her ignorance and errour; but hoping ſome good may be wrought upon her by reclaiming her from her wrong opinion, and inſtructing her in the knowledge of the truth, I am ſure you cannot be ſo much her enemy as to begrudge her the one, nor ſo uncharitable, as not to joyne your helping hand with ours in the other. Let not her ſimple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe cauſe in you either diſdaine, or contempt, and conſider that no one can preſume to know ſo much, but that there is a great deale more to learne, neither need you be aſhamed in ſomethings to be better informed. I confeſſe you are very zealous in your profeſſion, and (I beleeve) without diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation (and there cannot be too much zeale in matters that concerne immediately the glory of God) but in ſome cauſes zeale muſt be moderated with diſcretion, when a circumſtance may be uſed or not; and the worſhip of God no wayes leſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or the more furthered thereby;<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in which reſpect Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is better than Sacrifice. Beare you with <hi>Agnoa's</hi> infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as thoſe which are ſtronger beare with your weakneſſes. Conſider, we hate no ones perſon, but their ill qualities; and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:125649:24"/>
we judge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to be ſo bad, as to deny him our prayers, and endeavours for his amendment. His obſtinacie (when there is occaſion) ſhall not diminiſh our charity. Wee do not deteſt <hi>Idolana</hi> ſo much, as not to deſire, or be glad of her reformation in Doctrine and Manners. We depart only from her corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as ſhe is departed from the purer times, and Primitive Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors. We goe no further from the falſhood of her traditions, but as wee may come neerer to the truth of Gods Word. I wiſh her Doctrine were as conſonant unto ours, as ours is to the Scriptures, and ſo agreeing with Us in Ceremonies, as we are different from it in ſuperſtitions. Wee do not any good we do the more as in oppoſition to her, but becauſe it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded: and do not take the contrary of her actions to be the beſt rule to ſquare our devotions. Wherein ſhee erres not from the truth, wee may not diſſent from her. Who would hate the good conditions of any man for the reſt of the bad qualities in him? Who would faſt the rather, or eate f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon Fridaies, if the Papiſt ſhould eate nothing but fleſh that day? or who would make invitations the ſooner upon thoſe dayes deſigned by our adverſaries to abſtinence? Or, what Miniſter of the Goſpell would be the leſſe ſcrupulous to ſay his Service in white, if he did know a Prieſt of <hi>Idolana</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Cope or other like Veſtment to ſay his Maſſe in blacke? What hinderances are decent garments, and geſtures of the body to the devotions of the heart? whilſt I pray with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, heare for my edification, worſhip, and give thankes in ſpirit and truth? The habit may preſent it ſelfe to my eyes, it is the Doctrine ſhall goe to mine heart. Outward ſhewes and ceremonies, have their externall reſpects, and ſerve as handmaids to wait on, and not to ſit downe with Religion their Miſtreſſe. Now for theſe acts of indifferencie, ſhall not I doe what is good and commendable, becauſe the ill minded abuſe the ſame act to Will-worſhip and Superſtition? The Heathens of old had their Altars, Sacrifices, Temples, Prieſts. Did therefore the Patriarches, or Gods people of thoſe ages abſtaine from the worſhipping of God by Sacrifices upon Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars by prayers, and invocations in Temples, by their Prieſts: But as wee may not leave the uſe of any lawfull thing for the abuſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of it, ſo we may uſe a good thing in the ſame manner the wicked doth without offence, nay we ſhould offend if wee
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:125649:24"/>
did do it otherwiſe. And therefore if any Papiſt make his Prayer to God onely in the name of Chriſt, I may not pray otherwiſe. As farre in his Creed as hee goeth with the Word of God, and Orthodoxe conſent, I am to goe hand in hand with him. Nay if the devill himſelfe confeſſe Chriſt to be the Sonne of God, my confeſſion therefore muſt not be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. Perchance you are afraid by yeelding obedience to theſe indifferent ceremonies in reſpect of Religion you ſhall give of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence to a weake Chriſtian. But is it convenient that to fancie one you ſhould diſpleaſe a multitude, or for feare of offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Subject, care not to diſobey the command of your Magiſtrate? Shall not I bow or kneele to God in the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of holy duties, for feare leſt I give ſuſpition of Idolatry, becauſe the Heathens uſe this geſture in their Idolatrous ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations? Shall I not looke towards the Eaſt when I pray, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Pagans worſhip the riſing of the Sunne with their faces t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rned that way? nor to the Weſt for feare of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daiſme? to the North, leſt I ſeeme to reſpect the witches of <hi>Biarmia?</hi> nor to the South, leſt I be thought to favour the impoſture of <hi>Mahomet?</hi> Which way then ſhall I turne mine eyes when I worſhip? God ſees every where, his eyes are upon all the quarters of the world alike. What diſorder, <hi>Aſtene,</hi> would there be in Religion, to teach and allow obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence unto Princes, and yet reſerve a liberty to our ſelves of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringing his equall Lawes, and make ceremonies to be of the ſubſtance of Religion by denying an indifferencie in them; whileſt they trench not upon the rights of our beliefe, nor againſt good order, either in quantity or quality? Suppoſe the ſame, as I ſaid before, to be uſed by Idolaters, yet was <hi>Aſa</hi> and other Kings of Iſrael commended for pious: neither did the Prophets forſake their country or charges, although the high places were not taken away with the abuſes preſently. O <hi>Aſtene,</hi> diſdaine not the Church for her ſpots. Stumble not at ſtrawes to the griefe and diſturbance of Chriſtian peace. If your owne Conſcience cannot yet perſwade you of the truth of theſe things, ſeeke not to be maſter of anothers liberty, nor forſake not the ſociety of the Church, where there is agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the chiefe materials for meere circumſtances and formes. And where find you any preciſe Text for ſtanding more than kneeling, or for wearing of a blacke coat rather
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:125649:25"/>
than a white ſurpleſſe. In theſe things it is not good to be overwiſe: and if any will be contentious (ſaith not the leaſt of the Apoſtles) we have no ſuch cuſtome, nor the Churches of God. Be not ſo curious whilſt you view the Threſhold, to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect the inſide of the Temple: and whilſt you quarrell at what ſeemes wanting, you become ingratefull for what you have. Be thankfull for the free enjoyment of the meanes of ſalvation in the Word truly preached, and Sacraments duly adminiſtred. Hereabout ſpend thy thoughts, imploy thy meditations, &amp; accordingly bend all thy endeavours, &amp; pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes. Leave the government of the ſeverall Churches to their owne Magiſtrates, to whom it appertaines. Sticke not at names and degrees of authority in the Miniſtry, according to the eminencie of their gifts, and the bounty of their ſuperiours. If ſome be Doctors, other Paſtors, and Teachers, of a meaner ranke; if ſome be as Elders to rule and over-ſee, others but as Deacons and Miniſters, to be ſet on worke in the Lords vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard; all are but ſervants alike to their great Maſter, who doth imploy them, and muſt pay them their wages. A Biſhop, and every Miniſter have different reſpects in their functions concerning the Ceremonies, not the Doctrine of the Church: If they have any dignity above their fellow Embaſſadours, they have the greater charge impoſed upon them, and they exerciſe not Lordſhip over the Church, but as brethren rule with all humbleneſſe and integrity. And as their places are greater, their life and converſation is more illuſtrious: for they are as lights ſet upon the top of the hill, that they may be ſeene fartheſt; they are as eares and eyes, which members are placed in the higheſt part of the body, becauſe they are of chiefeſt uſe in the ſame. If they be not rightly qualified, as they ought, nor diſcharge the truſt committed unto them, as they ſhould, their title, and dignity will be more for their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, than their excuſe, and when the time of account commeth, that every man ſhall receive wages according to his worke, their candles ſhall be put out: when others that have beene more diligent and faithfull in the employment of their talents to their Maſters beſt advantage, for five ſhall receive ten; and in them the prediction of the Prophet ſhall be truly accompliſhed, They that be wiſe ſhall ſhine as the brightneſſe of the firmament, and they that turne many to righteouſneſſe, ſhall ſhine as the Starres for ever and ever.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:125649:25"/>Now <hi>Aſtene,</hi> I have beene the longer in my ſpeech, not to divert, but to direct thy zeale. and I muſt needs commend this in thee, that thou art not lukewarme in thy profeſſion: but I hope thou art not ſo much conceited of any perfection in thy wayes, as that thou needeſt not information: nor of ſo little charity to conſtrue theſe inſtructions in the worſt ſenſe, as to be ſwayed more by the cuſtome of the times, then the validity of truth and reaſon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aletheia</hi> had ſcarce ended, when <hi>Neophytes</hi> (who was there at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendant, and deſired to be retained for a Chapplaine to <hi>Alba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi>) ſaw that <hi>Aſtene</hi> was thus reproved, who had ſo often ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken exceptions (and not without cauſe) to ſome wild courſes of his, and that ſhe could not well reply to the reaſons of <hi>Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theia</hi> without cavill, or impertinencie, could not refraine from ſmiling, and withall to upbraid the modeſt virgin (which hee of all others had leaſt reaſon to do) with the ſtrictneſſe of her opinion; and now over ſtrait laced <hi>Aſtene,</hi> ſayes hee, you that are ſo preciſe, and ſuch a Puritan, have you nothing to ſay in the defence of your owne cauſe, and yet preſume to be an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructer of others? But when <hi>Aletheia</hi> perceived that <hi>Aſtene</hi> was much abaſhed at his reproofe, and that hee triumphed upon her weakneſſe, not for any love to the truth, but the more to bolſter up his owne looſneſſe, Fie <hi>Neophytes</hi> (ſaid ſhee) I am aſhamed that a man of your profeſſion and parts ſhould be thus light in your actions, and uncircumſpect in your ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. I ſee you do not conſider the dignity of your calling, nor the duty of your charge; the one doth require more gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity in your carriage, the other more charity in your words. Miniſters cannot be too cautious in their ſpeeches, and ſhould be as children and lambes without offence. A jeſt or ſcurrilous word towards the meaneſt of your brethren, ſhould be as farre from your tongues, as malice from your heart. It is more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couth (ſaid one well) to ſee a Miniſter wanton, or light in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, or behaviour, than it was for <hi>Socrates</hi> to ride upon a ſticke with children, or for old grave <hi>Cato</hi> to learne to fiddle. If <hi>Aſtene</hi> have offended (and her offence is the more pardona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, becauſe not wilfull) it ſhould be your part to pity her weakneſſe, not to make ſport of it; and ſeeke to informe her judgement better, by mild and loving admonitions, rather than to grieve her, or make her any way contemptible by
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:125649:26"/>
your ſcorne. But why tell I theſe things to you that know them ſo well, and teach them to others? But here <hi>Agnoa,</hi> who all this while had beene very attentive to what was ſpoken, could be no longer ſilent. The truth is (ſaid ſhee) the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon report is ſuch in <hi>Idolana,</hi> that the Preachers in <hi>Verana</hi> have as many Beliefes as Sects, and almoſt as many Sects as heads, ſo that every yeare they coyne ſome new point of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and their Miniſters, which are the ſetters abroach, and teachers thereof, do leaſt of all beleeve what they teach, for the moſt part are ſo licentious in their lives, and given to their eaſe and liberty, that it cannot be thought that they thinke that to be true in their hearts, which they ſpeake with their tongues. And this is the cauſe that many in <hi>Idolana</hi> are deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from conſenting with you in opinion, or of joyning with you in practiſe. Stay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Agnoa,</hi> not too faſt, ſaid <hi>Aletheia,</hi> the worſt ſpoake in the wheele creakes firſt: you are too credulous of reports, as of other your ſuperſtitions: and where you have the leaſt hint of any thing to worke upon, you will make of mole hils mountaines. I cannot excuſe the courſes, nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of many in <hi>Verana,</hi> that by the manner of their living lay themſelves open to cenſure and ſcandall. There is no Pomegranate wherein there may not be ſome graines rotten, but what is this to the ſound fruit? But if you will be impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall, and looke upon the manners of the Prieſts, and fraterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of moſt orders in <hi>Idolana,</hi> you ſhall find them farre to tranſcend in number, and nature the worſt of ours, and in ſome ſort to juſtifie their actions: but the corruption of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners (that they ſay and do not) doth not proceed from the purity of Doctrine in any profeſſours, nor the more prove it, I ſpeake not this to extenuate the faults of our Miniſters, or to aggravate thoſe of the Prieſts in <hi>Idolana.</hi> Where there is corn, there will be ſome tares in all fields; and for the diverſity of Sects, that are imputed to the diſgrace of <hi>Verana,</hi> whilſt our differences are about matters of circumſtance, and not of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, let the ſcandall returne from whence it came, and <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lana</hi> keepe it home to her ſelfe; whilſt her Doctrines are as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as her errours, and her errours ſo many, that it would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire more time than I meane to afford in counting the leaſt part of them.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Neophytes</hi> (ſaid ſhee) I would nevertheleſſe have you to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:125649:26"/>
be very carefull of your wayes, to be in no wiſe Cynicall, or ſurly in your carriage towards the meaneſt; that you give no juſt cauſe to the enemy to ſpeake ill of the truth by meanes of your converſation. Nor you, <hi>Aſtene,</hi> to wrangle ſo much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a ceremony, that the Doctrine be ill ſpoken of by your wilfull oppoſition. And I would have both preferre the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God, and the generall good of the Church before any private pleaſure or reſpects: and ſo farre condeſcend to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with each others weakneſſe, as God be not diſhonoured, nor the parcell of truth betrayed to the obloquy of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon enemy. And thinke not <hi>Neophytes,</hi> that I uſurpe this li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of ſpeech to diſparage your worth or calling: I know it is the moſt honourable of all others, and they that imploy themſelves diligently therein are worthy of double honour. You are, (if rightly qualified) the Embaſſadours of the moſt High God, and King of Kings, and cannot be ignorant what care and circumſpection there is required of Embaſſadors in their words and behaviour, leſt they be diſreſpected for the one, and their judgement queſtioned for the other. You are termed the <hi>Lights of the Word,</hi> and your light muſt not be hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den under a buſhel, but ſo <hi>ſhine before men that they may ſee your good workes, and glorifie your heavenly Father.</hi> Your light muſt be cleere as burning, for the candle muſt be ſet on a candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticke, and not have too much ſnuffe in it. You are called the ſalt of the earth, and therefore ought to be ſeaſoned with abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of knowledge to teach, with holineſſe of life to give ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, that you may be profitable to the Church, both by <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Converſation.</hi> You are named Shepheards, to lead your flocke in the right way, and to feed them in the beſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures. You are Gods husbandmen to dreſſe his vineyard, to worke in his harveſt; (<hi>the harveſt is great, the labourers are few</hi>) your time is but ſhort, your diligence muſt be the more in your ſtudy, in the Church, in viſiting the ſicke, and in all other practiſes of Piety, and Charity, that come within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe, and verge of your charge. But beware eſpecially of <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe,</hi> and ſeeke more the gaine of your peoples ſoules to God, than of their goods to your ſelves. If they be forgetfull of their duties, be not you therefore of yours. Be not tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported with paſſion, and no unſeemly, or uncharitable ſurmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in your Doctrine, nor conſume your precious time in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vectives
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:125649:27"/>
againſt the perſons of any, or in diſquiſition of imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent truthes, new opinions, ſchoole querkes, or needleſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies: but let the end of your calling alwaies have the chiefe place in your thoughts, and endeavours. And when you are in the Pulpit, you muſt have a grounded aſſurance for what you deliver: I would have you ſtrive to ſpeake to the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the Auditory, rather than to ſhew the ſtrength of your underſtanding: to deliver ſuch matter as may be more for their edification, than your owne applauſe: may more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit the heart, than fancie the eare, and ſhew that you ſeeke more to profit, than to pleaſe. So whilſt you ſtrive to glorifie God, and do good to his Church, you ſhall find your reward to be great, and your paines at laſt throughly recompenced: and therefore <hi>Neophytes,</hi> I hope you will take this advice in good part, and though you know better, what belongs to the diſcharge of your office (I ſhould count him an unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Miniſter, that is ignorant of that which hee hath under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken) it cannot be diſpleaſing unto you to be put in mind thereof, and to ſee what a friend thinks of it. I could ſay more, but you are of underſtanding to conceive what I would by the premiſes: and I could ſay no leſſe, ſuch is the love and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme I beare towards the encreaſe of religion, and honour of the Church.</p>
            <p>But no ſooner had <hi>Aletheia</hi> concluded this ſpeech, when the noyſe of the people (hearing of ſome hopes of <hi>Albania's</hi> reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very) that were come together to viſit her, was ſo great, and their deſire ſo earneſt to ſee their Lady on foot, whoſe health did ſo much concerne the ſafety of their eſtate, that <hi>Albania</hi> muſt of neceſſity preſent her ſelfe to the ſight of all, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhee (glad Lady) deſcending into the great Hall, where they waited her comming, and having received their preſents in ſigne of gratulation, ſhe lovingly thanked them all; and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a ſhort exhortation to them to continue in love and ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty amongſt themſelves, ſhe diſmiſſed them with great content: but a few of the better ſort ſhee cauſed to ſtay, and led them up to the Chamber where <hi>Aletheia</hi> was, to whoſe knowledge and acquaintance ſhee preſented and commended them, as ſome of her ſincere friends, and true well-wiſhers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aletheia</hi> who could ſoone dive into the diſpoſition of each nature, and knew how to accoſt each ſort with a due reſpect,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:125649:27"/>
giving to every of them a kinde ſalute, after ſome pauſe, when ſhe beheld that they earneſtly fixed their eyes on her, and were ſilent, and attentive to heare (for <hi>Abania</hi> had before prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them to that purpoſe, and requeſted <hi>Aletheia</hi> in their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe) what ſhe would ſay or command, to give both ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, ſhe thus began.</p>
            <p>My Maſters and Friends of <hi>Albania,</hi> happy in the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a gracious Soveraigne, and a fertile Country, I muſt needs commend your love to <hi>Albania,</hi> and care of her wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare. And to tell you the truth, ſhe hath beene of late afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a great diſtemper, and though the caſe be much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with her than it hath beene, through her Princes bounty, and the conſidence ſhe hath in the faire proceedings of a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Aſſembly: yet the meanes of a perfect cure and reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of her to her former ſtrenght, lyes mainely in your care, for the performance of ſuch duties towards God, and your King, as Religion, and loyalty bindes you to. And give me leave, ſince you offered me the occaſion, to tell you without flattery, that the chiefe roote of all your miſeries is in your ſelves; and therefore, I would not have you out of any ſelfe-love, or ſiniſter reſpect, wholly to lay the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of this great miſ-happe befalne to <hi>Albania,</hi> upon for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine or higher cauſes, (though theſe may be made inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments thereof, juſtly for your puniſhment) nor for the reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to depend principally upon any earthly meanes, no not the Policy and Honeſty of the wiſeſt heads in your Aſſembly, (their knowledge and power is but humane, they are men, and may erre) but you muſt looke home, and reflect your thoughts upon the conſideration of your owne wayes for the one, and with humble mindes, lift up your mindes higher, to be made partakers of the other. There is a juſt God above that hath beene, and daily is, offended with your hainous miſcarriages, and wherein have not the beſt of you, ſome wayes offended his Divine Majeſty? Of ill thoughts and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret tranſgreſſions, you are moſt conſcious your ſelves, but thoſe vices which walke in publique view, and are acted in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen face of the Sunne, amongſt all ſorts of people, more or leſſe, doe convince the truth of what I ſpeake, and to which your owne conſciences cannot but be witneſſes. Is not Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry growne to that height, almoſt to counterchecke true
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:125649:28"/>
Religion amongſt you by the encreaſe of Popery. Are not the Articles of our Beliefe queſtioned? Is not Religion min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and new faſhioned by ſome that take too much liberty, to dally with matters of conſcience? I appeale to thoſe which are learned, which are like the Sunne, whoſe brightneſſe all admire, but no one can endure to looke upon. Priefely, I cannot ſtand to make a catalogue of vices; Is there not much murmuring, diſtruſt, and oppreſſion in your griping Uſurer, and covetous Officers? Is there not exceſſive Pride, covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe (which <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in his Politiques calleth the Extremity of Poverty) gluttony (with luſt and idleneſſe, its conſequences) in the wealthy? Is there not much malice, envy, and ambition, in ſuch as ſo greedily ſeeke after preferment and promotion? Is there not too much equivocation and falſhood in the Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to ſell his wares, and vent his commodities? Is there not too much blaſphemy, cruelty, and rapine in the Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, that followes the warre in a deſperate mood, onely to kill or he killed? What contention and multitude of Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites for want of Charity, doe abound in every corner? How hard hearted are many, in giving of almes, or relieving the wants of a diſtreſſed Brother? What neglect and forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity in Cods Worſhip? How unaccuſtomed and dull are the ſpirits of moſt in the performing their ordinary workes of Devotion, and about Religious Exerciſes? I doe touch at the heads: There are ſo many inſtances, and ſo well knowne to you of particulars, that I ſhall but needleſly trouble you and <hi>Albania</hi> with their repetition. But inſtead of avoyding ſuch and the like abuſes, many are come to this height of impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, as to ſhadow their vices under the habit of vertues. Drunkenneſſe paſſeth with them for good fellowſhip: Prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gality is tearmed bounty: Covetouſneſſe miſnamed good huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry: Ambition hath the note of a brave mind and gallant ſpirit: Revenge is eryed up for the marke of valour and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of Honour: Pride is accounted faſhionable hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fomneſſe and decency: Extortion and Oppreſſion denote much policy and worldly wiſedome. When, on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, in religious matters, Vertues are commonly doſamed with the ſtaine of their oppoſite vidos So be that is Zealous in his Profeſſion, is counted factious: He that reproves the ſinnes and cnormities of the time, a buſie-body: If a man
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:125649:28"/>
partake not in leudneſſe with ſuch as tempt him to beare them company therein, 'tis by reaſon of ſome ſelfe-conceit: If a man put up an injury, ſuffer an affront, he is eſteemed a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, or of a baſe ſpirit: If he be liberall to thoſe that want, heis a waſter, and careleſſe ſpender of his eſtate, and may want himſelf before he dye: If he be temperate, continent, and ſpend not his time jovially in merry compauy, and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtime, he is thought to be proud, ſingular, or melancholicke: His Devotion is condemned for hypocriſie, his reproofe goes for malice; what is reaſon in others, in him is but opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: Whereas the ſame man, would he but flatter, and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour men in their conditions, beare with their manners, and applaud all their courſes, this were the onely man, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy all reſpect. I ſpeake not theſe things, as accuſing you to be guilty, although I know, you are ſomewhat too confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable to the times, and too much ſeeke your owne eaſe. The publike good is more in your talke, but I doubt me your pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate gaine is more in your aime. But if it goe not well with the generall, your caſe muſt needes be lameutable. And there fore, I would have you timely redreſſe ſuch errors, as you finde your ſelves to be moſt guilty of, and reclaime others by your counſell and perſwaſions. You muſt not make any arme of fleſh your ſtay, nor lay any falſe grounds in your imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, that if things ſucceed according to your fancy, all will be well. Whilſt God is offended, nothing can conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue long well: therefore he muſt in the firſt place, and at all times be ſought unto, by teares and Prayers. You muſt meet him with red eyes, blubbered cheekes, pale viſage, penſive ſoule, proteſtations of humility, importunities for mercy. There muſt be a true humiliation for ſinnes paſt, a ſetled pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of amendment. You muſt pinion the wings of all high conceites of your owne worth, and expiate fore-paſt vices, with a ſacrifice of the contrary vertues: And then I will aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure you, that if all the forces of the world were banded a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you for your overthrow; if all the ſubtill braines, and politique <hi>Machiavilians</hi> of <hi>Idolana</hi> were ſet together on worke, their cloſe or open plots to ſubvert your Religion, or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dammage your ſtate, ſhould prove but ſpiders webbes or twiſts of hempe with <hi>Achitophel</hi> and <hi>Haman,</hi> to choke their Authors: You ſhall enjoy your Liberties, Priviledges, Religion, Peace,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:125649:29"/>
with as great freedome as heretofore.</p>
            <p>And now in the ſecond place, I muſt adviſe you, as you be carefull to give unto God thoſe things which are Gods: ſo to render thoſe things which are <hi>Caeſars,</hi> unto <hi>Caeſar,</hi> cuſtome to whom cuſtome, tribute to whom tribute belongeth. You muſt acknowledge (as loyall Subjects) that your King is Gods ſupreame Deputy, ſet over you to rule and governe you in all matters, Civill and Eccleſiaſticke. You may not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe him, in what manner you will be ruled, nor by what meanes. You may conteſt with him, if he offer wrong, by way of Supplication, and not of Diſpute. If his Commands be juſt, you muſt willingly obey them: and herein what he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joynes ſtrictly, you muſt, according to the utmoſt of your power, readily put in execution. But if he command any thing directly againſt the glory of God, the contrary of which God commands, <hi>Whether it be better to obey God or Men, judge you.</hi> But in this caſe, there muſt be ſufferance of the penalty, and no reſiſtance againſt the authority of your Prince. And for the wrong he ſeekes to doe you, you muſt ſeeke to God, to ſet him in the Right, though he take away your Liberties, Goods, and lives, contrary to all Lawes and Equity: Yea, even to thoſe, the performance of which (though by force he may not be conſtrayned) in Conſcience he is bound. Yet you muſt not curſe him in your heart, nor touch a lap of his garment with ſuch a thought, for he is the Lords Anointed. But what ſpend I breath in theſe things? You have a Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and gracious Prince, one that is zealous of Gods Glory, and will be carefull of your good. You need not feare that he will be perſwaded to any thing that ſhall oppoſe the one, or hinder the other. He will not wrong his owne Soule, to hurt you in your Eſtates, or Perſons. Hee well knowes, that though he is not to be accountable to men, he hath a wiſer, and ſtricter Judge (if he doe not execute the charge commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto him, in ſome ſort as he ſhould) will call him to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count at laſt, becauſe this High place and Authority over o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, was not committed unto him for his owne pleaſure and eaſe, but for his Maſters glory, and the benefit of the Church. And therefore, Prayers and Supplications ought to be made inceſſantly unto God, for his preſervation and ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty above all others: For where the Prince is good, that peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:125649:29"/>
of all others have moſt cauſe to rejoyce, and bleſſe God for him, and ſtrive to pleaſe him in all his juſt deſires. And in this reſpect, it muſt be farre from you to wiſh him any ill, to ſpeake of him without beſeeming reſpect, much more to joyne in any councell or confederacy with his enemies, and moſt of all to take up armes, except at his Command, and for his defence. You ought not to murmure againſt his proceedings, nor ſpeake ill of his Officers, or Commiſſioners, upon every ſleight ſuſpicion.</p>
            <p>Charity will counterpoiſe the diſtractions of many occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences: but raſhneſſe, and inconſiderateneſſe in judgement, is an impetuous Paſſion, which beares downe all Reaſon. When things goe not as they ſhould, and you know not who is in blame; cry downe no man meerely upon report, but leave offenders to the tryall of the Lawes, by their competent Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. But when you are required, or any thing comes to your knowledge, which may prove dangerous to the State, not to be partiall in Affection, to tremble at the ſight of a high Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, or guild a mudded wall, or feare the countenance of any man; (For time and juſtice will weare out the dreames and plots of wicked policy, and ſtrenghten the faire proceedings of Truth and Honeſty) but boldly and impartially to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover what you know. And whenſoever it ſhall be thought fit by the States and Commons, and that the Kings neceſſities and occaſions ſo require, to be furniſhed with a ſupply of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies; that then without further queſtion, you cheerefully contribute what ſhall be ſo impoſed: And by your voluntary benevolences, as time and your abilities ſhall give you leave to teſtifie that true affection and love to him, which you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend.</p>
            <p>And theſe ſupplies will be with farre greater eaſe disburſed, if you pleaſe to ſubſtract but ſomewhat from your ſuperflui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: turne ſome of your exceſſive and often feaſtings into faſts, or fewer diſhes: take ſomething from the price and trimming of your garments. Uſe ſuch as may ſerve for decency and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience: but be not like Antiques or like Apes to follow e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very new faſhion. Reſtraine ſomewhat from your gamings and expences of idle houres. Your appetite ſhall be never the leſſe ſatisfied, and your bodies more healthy. Your attire ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to your degree and calling ſhall not a jot be the more
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:125649:30"/>
indecent, nor your bodies the leſſe warme.</p>
            <p>Beſides, the more Velvets and Silkes are forborne, our owne cloathes ſhall be in weare, and the poore better ſet on<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> worke in making of them. You ſhall finde wayes enough of more thrifty recreation, and have more comfort in the redeeming of your pretious time, then in any miſpending of it. And now I have ſhewed you my adviſe as plainely as I can: and (it being my uſe, howſoever it be taken, to doe good unto all, as occaſion ſhall be offered) as I held my ſelfe in duty bound. And with this ſhe pauſed, and they that heard her with great content, tooke their leave, with promiſe for their parts, and in the behalfe of the reſt that were abſent, to be more carefull of their carriage, and reſpectfull of their duty towards God and their Soveraigne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aletheia,</hi> likewiſe would have taken her leave of <hi>Albania</hi> for ſome time, ſeeing her well onwards on the mending hand, but was interrupted by an occaſion, which was unworthy her ſtay, or the relation, but that you may ſee what cruelty there is in the nature of a covetous wretch.</p>
            <p>Thus it happened, <hi>Albania's</hi> ſervants hearing a great la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation and cry at their Ladies gate, went forth to ſee what it meant. Where they ſaw two Sergeants dragging a poore man to priſon for anothers debt, who deſired that <hi>Albania</hi> would take ſome pity on his caſe, and his Wife, and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren that made this great moane, with earneſt entreaties and teares beſought the like. Whereupon one of the ſervants cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Eleos,</hi> ran in preſently, and acquainted his Lady with their requeſt, who beingſtill ready to further a worke of Charity, (and the rather becauſe <hi>Aletheia</hi> was then in place) gave pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent command that they ſhould bring the Priſoner, and the party that ſought this extremity againſt him, to her preſence, and ſhe would requeſt <hi>Aletheia</hi> to be Judge in the cauſe: ſo by vertue of her command, the parties were both brought where the Ladies were. And truely the covetous wretch would not by any intreaties have beene perſwaded to have come of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, ſo much did he abhorre the company of ſuch as were charitably minded, and was ſo afraid to looke Authority in the face: but by the way he could not forbeare curſing, and ſwearing, with fearefull imprecations, that hee would not loſe a penny by any man. In the meane while, the poore
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:125649:30"/>
man had acquainted the Ladies that the debt was none of his owne; but that he had ingaged himſelfe by Bond to ſee him paid: that the debt was but ſmall at the firſt, but that it had runne on ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rre, that the Uſe exceeded the Principall: and the Creditour might have had his money long ere this, but that he was careleſſe to take it in upon his Security, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended when he ſaw time to take his beſt advantage: and that he now ſued him (whiles the Principall had wherewith to ſatisfie) who was unable, if he ſhould fell all he had, to pay ſo great a ſumme, and if he were laid in priſon, his Wife, and Children were quite undone. This hard caſe of the poore man, and cruelty of the other, drew teares of pity from the eyes of the compaſſionate Ladies, and with all anger and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine, forced a red colour in their cheekes. Thou unnaturall wretch (ſaid <hi>Aletheia</hi>) what moved thee to be ſo hard hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt a poore man that owes thee nothing, nor hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing to pay?</p>
            <p>The cruel <hi>Plutos,</hi> for ſo was he named, as wretched in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, as crooked in Limbes, and wrinckled in countenance; as miſerable in ſoule and poore in goodneſſe, as ragged and patched in garments, could not deny what the poore man ſaid, nor<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> would make any direct anſwer, to what was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, but ſtill he inſiſted upon this tone, <hi>Give me my money,</hi> I will have the forfeiture of my Bonds, and Mortgages; I will be paid the Intereſt of my monies to a Farthing. To a farthing! (ſaid <hi>Alitheia</hi>) is this thy Religion? Religion! (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed he) tell them of Religion that care for it; <hi>Let me have my Money.</hi> Vile Atheiſt (ſaid ſhe) doſt thou preferre thy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> traſh and pelfe before the Service of God, and thy ſalvation? Yea (ſaid the Ideot) that I doe, and before Heaven alſo. This<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> world I know, that other I doe not. God grant me to live ſtill on earth, let him keepe Heaven for himſelfe. Speake of me what you will, ſo I may gaine by it. If you be all hanged or drowned, I care not. Let this poore foole that had no more wit, but to bring himſelfe within danger of my mercy, rot in Priſon. Let his Wife and Children ſtarve, let all his friends curſe me, I ſhall thrive never the worſe. Theſe, and other like devilliſh ſpeeches<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> this Earthworme uttered, ſo that <hi>Alba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi> paled, <hi>Aletheia</hi> was ſore afrighted, and both could not endure to heare the Monſter any longer, but commanded the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:125649:31"/>
poore man to be ſet at liberty, and ſent him home with ſome gifts to boot.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aletheia</hi> would have given ſome counſell to the wretch, but thinking it not fit at this time to caſt Pearle befo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Swine, ſhe bid them caſt him out upon the Dung-hill among his compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and in the meane while keepe him there, till ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther puniſhment might be deviſed for him, and ſuch like, by the Honorable Court of Parliament.</p>
            <p>And ſurely it would draw a great bleſſing upon this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, if his Majeſty and Councell would take into their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration the cruell wayes of oppreſſion and vexation uſed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the poorer ſort, and other by thoſe who, that they may raiſe a great eſtate to themſelves, care not how they come by it, though it be with the ruine of whole Familes.</p>
            <p>But whileſt the Ladies were thus diſquieted by the late e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, <hi>Chronos</hi> was come in poſt to fetch <hi>Aletheia</hi> to the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Aſſembly, who at this time greatly needed her preſence. Who preſently went away with him, having taken leave of <hi>Albania,</hi> and left her in the company of <hi>Agatha</hi> and <hi>Fidelia,</hi> and many other of her truſty ſervants, to whom <hi>Albania</hi> committing the care of her affaires, and ſhutting the doores of her Chamber, lay downe upon her Couch a while to take ſome repoſe, and being laid, fell into a ſweet ſleepe. But the Ladies that ſtaid by her, rejoycing that their Lady tooke her reſt ſo quietly, and that a ſmall noyſe would not awake her, tooke each her Inſtrument, and having plaid a while thereon, and ſeeing <hi>Albania</hi> ſtirred not the while, began altogether thus to ſing.</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>COme Sions Singers, ſit all round,</l>
                  <l>And each with voyce and inſtrument,</l>
                  <l>The ſweeteſt ſtraines of muſicke ſound,</l>
                  <l>That Art, or fancy can invent.</l>
                  <l>And all together loudly ſing</l>
                  <l>The praiſes of our Heavenly King.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:125649:31"/>
                  <l>Likewiſe ye holy Shepherd ſwaines,</l>
                  <l>Well skill'd in Songs and Temple-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ayes,</l>
                  <l>Whileſt that your flockes graze on the Plaines,</l>
                  <l>Chaunt bymnes unto Jehovahs praiſe.</l>
                  <l>And let the Quire with Ecchoes ring</l>
                  <l>Of praiſes of our Heavenly King.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Deare Heraulds of our God proclaime,</l>
                  <l>In thoſe aſſemblies where you meete,</l>
                  <l>The joy of our Hieruſalem,</l>
                  <l>With Hallelujahs publiſh it:</l>
                  <l>That all which heare the ſame, may ſing</l>
                  <l>The praiſes of our heavenly King.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Each age, each ſex, and each degree,</l>
                  <l>That love their King, the Church and State,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe hopes return'd with joy may ſee,</l>
                  <l>Were almoſt gone and loſt of late.</l>
                  <l>Then have not all juſt cauſe to ſing</l>
                  <l>The praiſes of our heavenly King?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Me thought of late mine eyes did marke</l>
                  <l>A gentle dove fly through the ayre,</l>
                  <l>With Olive branch, when the ſhrill Larke</l>
                  <l>To heaven-ward flew chirping, where</l>
                  <l>Angels and Saints in Anthemes ſing</l>
                  <l>The praiſes of our heavenly King.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Cheare up ſad hearts and you ſhall ſee</l>
                  <l>All ſtormes of feare will ſhortly ceaſe:</l>
                  <l>Your ſighs to ſongs ſhall turned be,</l>
                  <l>And tales of warre to tunes of Peace.</l>
                  <l>Inſtead of mourning all ſhall ſing</l>
                  <l>The praiſes of our Heavenly King.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Winter laſts not all the yeare,</l>
                  <l>The longeſt night muſt yeeld to day,</l>
                  <l>When that the Sunne begins to cleare,</l>
                  <l>All miſts and clouds muſt packe away.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:125649:32"/>And now is time for us to ſing</l>
                  <l>The praiſes of our Heavenly King.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Sleepe on <hi>Albania,</hi> worthy Dame,</l>
                  <l>And in thy Princes grace be bold;</l>
                  <l>Thoſe wiſh'd thy woes ſhall find their ſhame,</l>
                  <l>Their plots of miſchiefe will not hold.</l>
                  <l>They now ſhall waile, but thou ſhalt ſing</l>
                  <l>The praiſes of our heavenly King.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>God bleſſe King, Lords, and Commons all,</l>
                  <l>With hearts true love, and mindes conſent.</l>
                  <l>Let no miſchance to them befall,</l>
                  <l>Whileſt that they ſit in <hi>Parliament.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>So ſhall King, Lords, and Commons ſing</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Praiſes of our Heavenly King.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>ANd now <hi>Albania,</hi> whether ſatisfied with the ſweet repoſe ſhe had taken, or wakened with the pleaſant muſicke of the voyces, ſtart up as from a trance with this joyfull Accla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</p>
            <p>Ah happy <hi>Albania,</hi> happy Soveraigne, and happy <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nita!</hi> and this ſhe uttered with a moſt chearefull countenance (the Index of a like heart) and hereupon pauſed; when to her Ladies deſiring to know the reaſon of this her exultation, ſhe thus replyed, that ſhe had great cauſe to ſpeake what ſhe did, find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her ſtate ſo well amended in all parts, and ſhe could not in few words expreſſe the comfort ſhe felt, and conceived by this alteration, and thought ſhe ſhould be hardly able to put a temper to the exceſſe, but that the remembrance of her for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer griefes and miſhaps, and the danger of relapſe, through a careleſſe ſecurity, together with thoſe concernenences to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards her Lord and Maſter, in reſpect of her duty and due ſervices in a moſt exact obedience, required a moderation in her delights, and a circumſpection in her behaviour; but fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:125649:32"/>
ſhe had ſomewhat exceeded, and had beene too paſſionate in the expreſſion of her late complaints (which ſhe imputed to the tenderneſſe of her nature, having not of a long time beene uſed to ſuch changes) ſhe deſired the favour of the beſt interpretation, proteſting withall, that howſoever her ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches might ſeeme to ſavour of too much bitterneſſe againſt ſome delinquents, her aime herein was not to particulars, nor ſo much againſt the perſons of any, as their offences, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deſerved the greater pardon; and well conſidering that <hi>Humanum eſt errare,</hi> ſhe hoped the parties guilty would not be ſo deſperate to proceed on farther in thoſe wicked courſes, ſo clearely diſcovered, but ſpeedily retire, and caſt themſelves downe at the feet of his Majeſties clemency, and make ſome recompence to the injuryed parties, by their ſincere amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and provident endeavours for the common good: and as for thoſe loyall hearts (the conſtant friends and joynt pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuers of hers and her ſiſters welfare) and un-interrupted hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe (having eſcaped the ſtorme at home by the miraculous providence of the Almighty Lord,) ſhe deſired them to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing the more ſecure in their vigilant care of future occurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, having alwayes a provident eye, both at ſhore and to ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, for the timely prevention of ſuch inconveniences as might ſteale on them in their owne, or be intended againſt them from forraine parts. And now <hi>Veridicus</hi> was returned from the Aſſembly, and upon notice was quickely admitted, where he much rejoyced to ſee how the cauſe ſtood with <hi>Alba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> and deſiring to have ſome conference with her in private, the Ladies gave place, having firſt demanded how things went and received onely this anſwer, Good Newes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Which the Lord long continue to his glory, the Kings honour, and the Kingdomes ſafety.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="explanation">
            <pb facs="tcp:125649:33"/>
            <head>An Explanation of the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for ſome of the Appellations in this Treatiſe contained.</head>
            <list>
               <item>ALbania, <hi>From the white cliffes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Megala, <hi>From the large extent.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Aquilina <hi>From the Enſignes of the Eagle, and Flower de Luce.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Liliana <hi>From the Enſignes of the Eagle, and Flower de Luce.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Verana, <hi>From part of Chriſtendome, which profeſſeth Religion ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the truth of Scripture.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Regicida, <hi>From the doctrine of King-killing.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Idolana, <hi>From the frequency and diverſity of image-adorations in that City.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Agatha, <hi>The two properties of a good Servant, according to that,</hi> Well done thou good and faithfull Servant.</item>
               <item>Fidelia, <hi>The two properties of a good Servant, according to that,</hi> Well done thou good and faithfull Servant.</item>
               <item>Agnoa, <hi>From that the Papiſts hold ignorance to be the mother of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Aſtene, <hi>From the tenderneſſe of Cenſcience about things indifferent.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sympathia, <hi>From the requiſites of Charity, and true Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Agape, <hi>From the requiſites of Charity, and true Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sophia, <hi>From the conditions of wiſedome and modeſty, neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for ſuch as are employd in Embaſſages.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sophroſyne, <hi>From the conditions of wiſedome and modeſty, neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for ſuch as are employd in Embaſſages.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Plutos, <hi>From the inordinate love of gaine, and devilliſh wayes for at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of the ſame.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The other denominations ſo ſpeake themſelves, as they need no further explication.</p>
            <closer>Soli Deo laus,</closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
